<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Sapientia justificata, or, A vindication of the fifth chapter to the Romans and therein of the glory of the divine attributes, and that in the question or case of original sin, against any way of erroneous understanding it, whether old or new : more especially, an answer to Dr. Jeremy Taylors Deus justificatus / by John Gaule ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A42503</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G378</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R5824</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13693239</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13693239</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">101412</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42503)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101412)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 844:1)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Sapientia justificata, or, A vindication of the fifth chapter to the Romans and therein of the glory of the divine attributes, and that in the question or case of original sin, against any way of erroneous understanding it, whether old or new : more especially, an answer to Dr. Jeremy Taylors Deus justificatus / by John Gaule ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[10], 117 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for N. Paris and Tho. Dring ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1657.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667. --  Deus justificatus.</TERM><TERM>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans V --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</TERM><TERM>Sin, Original --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2000-00</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2001-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2001-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP Staff (Michigan)</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2001-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP Staff (Michigan)</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2001-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A42503">
<STC T="W">G378</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13693239</BIBNO>
<VID>101412</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Sapientia Iustificata, OR, A Vindication of the fifth Chapter to the ROMANS:</P>
<P>And therein of the Glory of the Divine Attributes, and that in the Question or Case of <HI>Original Sin,</HI> a∣gainst any way of Erroneous under∣standing it, whether old or new.</P>
<P>More especially an Answer to Dr. <HI>Ieremy Taylors</HI> DEUS IUSTIFICATUS,</P>
<P>By <HI>Iohn Gaule,</HI> Minister of great <HI>Staughton</HI> in the County of <HI>Huntingdon.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>N. Paris</HI> and <HI>Tho. Dring,</HI> and are to be sold at the <HI>George</HI> in <HI>Little Brit∣tain,</HI> and at the <HI>George</HI> in <HI>Fleetstreet,</HI> near St. <HI>Dunstans</HI> Church. 1657.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epigraph">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<P>DIcitis nos asserendo Peccatum original<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> — Deum crimine iniquitatis arguere — Nos ergo dicimus, nec iniquus est Deus cum peccatis sive originalibus sive propriis digna retribuit, magisque aut iniquus, aut infirmus ostenditur, si jugum grave su∣per filios <HI>Adam</HI> à die (sicut scriptum est) nativitatis eorum, usque in diem sepulturae in matre omnium; sub quo jugo Imago eju atteritur, aut ipse (nullo originali vel pro prio precedente peccato) aut quilibet aliu ipso imponit invito. — Deus autem justus s<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tanta parvulis mala (quanta nunc dicere non sufficio) nihil peccati trahentibus irro∣gerat, magis appareret injustus.</P>
<BIBL>Aug<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cont. Julian: Pelagian. lib. X.</BIBL>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To his much honoured and most worthy Friend IOHN BALDVVIN Esquire.</HEAD>
<P><HI>Noble Sir,</HI></P>
<P>HOw oft, how much in our seri∣ous discourses up∣on more than one of this Authors works, have we honoured
<PB REF="3"/>
him for his learning; affe∣cted him for his piety; ad∣mired him for his industry; ap∣plauded him for his eloquence; and condoling him, pitied his sufferings, among many o∣ther godly and learned men his like? and thereupon it was that we studiously laboured, not so much to reconcile with∣in our selves many a particular phrase and passage (dispersed here and there) seeming not only to be borrowed from, but as bordering too much upon the expressions, if not opinions of the <HI>Inorthodox</HI>; but rather to salve them up to others un∣derstandings, who began to take more scandal at them,
<PB REF="3"/>
than we our selves did; and this we endeavoured in a can∣did interpretation of his inten∣tion, as one who meant only to make use of the Adversaries manner of speaking to no other purpose, but to cause (I say not his, but) their forms and affectations to speak (as near as possibly could be) to the te∣nor of the <HI>Orthodox Truth</HI> and <HI>Faith</HI> in general, and to that of the <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>England</HI> in more e∣special.</P>
<P>But truly, Sir, this little piece of his, which you were lately pleased to send me; puts me ut∣terly to a loss; and sets me so quite beyond the seeking for an excuse; that it forces me alto∣gether
<PB REF="4"/>
to fall upon a dissent. I could heartily have wish'd, that instead of answering his Friends (learned Friends) ob∣jection, he would rather have sate down by their advice; For were the thing that he princi∣pally aims at, true, yet was it not so necessary to be brought to light, especially not under the notion of a charge or chal∣lenge; For he may well assure himself all the reformed Di∣vines (men <HI>Orthodox</HI> and mo∣derate, both for <HI>Doctrine</HI> and <HI>Discipline</HI>) cannot chose but take themselves stricken at through the <HI>Presbyterians sides</HI>: And therefore, notwithstand∣ing he entitles it (<HI>Deus justifica∣tus</HI>)
<PB REF="4"/>
against them only, yet I am much afraid he will not therein prove <HI>Homo justificandus,</HI> neither in their judgement, nor of many others, and they his friends and fellow workers, and fellow-sufferers too, whe∣ther more or less made known unto him.</P>
<P>And now (judicious Sir) though your own judgement (both in Divinity, and for o∣ther good learning) be such as come short to few of your qua∣lity; and so well known (as I need not speak) to the Gentle∣men of your Countrey and o∣thers; yet forasmuch as I am your Minister, I know you ex∣pect my mind; for therefore
<PB REF="5"/>
I received it at your hand. And verily I shall (by Gods Grace) dissemble it neither with him, nor you; yet I would have both him and you think, I dare not presume to propound any thing here upon my own mind alone, but as I am ena∣bled to goe along with the Scriptures and the Church of God. Because it is a hard matter in (such a hard point as this of Original Sin) for a man to goe alone, and not to erre. Neverthelesse I know (through the gift of God) a man may be enabled and enlarged to speak newer and clearer; but then he must be sure that his ground for the
<PB REF="5"/>
Point be old, and good; For it is a <HI>Fanaticism</HI> for any man to con∣ceit that God concealed such a main Principle of his Truth from his whole Church, till now that he revealed it to himself alone.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="section">
<PB REF="6"/>
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>A VINDICATION OF THE Fifth Chapter TO THE ROMANS.</HEAD>
<P>FIrst let me begin with his Title and his Scope, &amp; compare them both together, that so we may see how answera∣ble they are each to o∣ther; For let me tell you, Sir, (and you shall observe it in all the ridiculous, sensless, fanatical facti∣ous, heretical and blasphemous Pam∣phlets of these our evil days) that fair Titles are taken up only to palliate false and foul intents, neither is there any shorter or surer way of refuting an Er∣ror, than in searching directly how all the intended scribbling agrees little or
<PB N="2" REF="7"/>
nothing with the pretended superscrip∣tion. For let truths be spoken, yet they are not so there, unless they be accor∣ding to the main purpose to which they are intituled. This Authors Title or superscription is (<HI>Deus justificatus</HI>) now I pray God it prove so the whole work throughout; For I greatly suspect that the main intention of this discourse will but work to frustrate the title that is gi∣ven to it, because I perceive his princi∣pal Scope and Conclusion is, to make O∣riginal sin to be a sin so called by a <HI>Me∣tonymie</HI> only, for he very often denies it to be a sin, properly, really, formally, and inherently, and contends mainly to have it no more but a <HI>Metonymical Im∣putation</HI> to certain purposes, which are very involved words, and are so studi∣ously covert, as if he were afraid or a∣shamed to speak plainly outright. But this is as much as to say, That where Ori∣ginal sin is called sin, it is not so literally and properly, but only is called so (by a figurative form of locution) by a Meto∣nymie of the cause for the effect, namely, sin put only for the punishment of sin, and the imputation of this sin by God, is no more, but the infliction of the pu∣nishment;
<PB N="3" REF="7"/>
And this punishment is with limitation to certain purposes, and those purposes are no further, but to Tempo∣ral misery and Death. Gather all these together, and you shall so come to plain speaking, <HI>viz.</HI> That Original sin is no such thing, but hath only the name or appellation of sin in a translated sense, but directly it is either no sin, or ano∣thers, and not ours. And therefore the Divine imputation is not of the guilt and corruption to us, but all is an infliction only of the punishment and suffering on us, yet so as that it is confined to a temporal death: If this be not the summary drift, let the whole book speak, but if this make to the Title, now give me leave to speak. How invective is this Vindicator of the Divine Attri∣butes against the Sublapsarians, and yet, (this I'll say for them) they doe not, they dare not include any under the se∣vere Decree of the Divine Justice, till they have considered all as born under the lapse and guilt, and defection and infection of Original sin; Whereas he himself will not have Original sin so much as properly so called, neither will he have any to be so considered unde<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="4" REF="8"/>
the lapse as really under the guilt or fault; yet notwithstanding he will have the Divine Imputation or Decree to de∣scend even upon all, for matter of Tem∣poral infliction, Now judge whether of these two Sentences or Executions can more prejudice or impeach the Divine attributes of Justice, Wisdom, Good∣ness, &amp;c. <HI>viz.</HI> That of Gods imputing the whole and utter punishment unto some, together with the real imputati∣on of the sin, or that of Gods imputing but part of the punishment, even unto All; and that without any real imputa∣on of the sin at all? Certainly the Di∣vine Justice is made to labour more un∣der this charge for punishing all (though but Temporally) where he takes none to be faulty; than it can under that for punishing but some (although eternally) where it finds all guilty. Thus forcing at his own aim, and yet, forgetting the mark prefixed, he miserably impinges upon the same Rock himself, which he would insimulate others for to dash upon.</P>
<P>Would he verily and indeed have vin∣dicated the glory of the Divine attri∣butes in the question of Original sin, he
<PB N="5" REF="8"/>
should not have proposed to do it on∣ly against the Presbyterian way of un∣derstanding it, (who had they no more disturbed the wholsom Disci∣pline of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> than they have of late directly publiquely, and with one consent) opposed her in her sound Doctrine, she had never been thus widowed to such disorder and di∣stress, but might have sat still a Queen of Reformed Churches, flourishing in her Peace and Truth: Neither will they all yield, that their way of understanding it should ever be pointed out for a way a part, or singular from the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and other Reformed Chur∣ches, but he should rather have taken such a kind of Vindication in hand a∣gainst the Pelagian, the Manichaean, the Samosatenean, the Socinian, the Pon∣tifician, the Pighian, the Flaccian, the Arminian, the Supralapsarian; yea the Judaical, the Philosophical, the Schola∣stical, the Synergistical, and the Ana∣baptistical way of understanding it; all which Hereticks and Sectaries have here (would a man goe about to make an ex∣act Catalogue or Computation) in more than sixteen times sixteen famous (that
<PB N="6" REF="9"/>
is infamous) questions, opinions, errors, trench'd too palpably and grosly upon the glory of the Divine attributes in∣deed. As, be pleased to take here a taste. What but their own way of understan∣ding it caused the Jews to run into some error about Orignal sin? as that some are born in sin, and others not; again, that some are wholly so born, and o∣thers but in part, else how is it they say, <HI>Thou wast altogether born in sin?</HI> Ioh. 9. 34. objecting this scornfully to another in an Exemption of and difference to themselves? and again, That a Typical, a legal or an external Covenant was suf∣ficient to free them from it, without the truth of Christ, and his Gospel of Grace, otherwise, why said they within them∣selves, <HI>We have</HI> Abraham <HI>to our Father?</HI> Mat. 3. 9. and boasted before others, <HI>We be</HI> Abrahams <HI>seed, we be not born of For∣nication.</HI> Ioh. 8. 33, 41. and why doth Christ (in convincing them) bring them to the Original of sin? <HI>Ye are of your Fa∣ther the Devil, and the lusts of your Fa∣ther ye will doe, for he was a Murtherer from the beginning, &amp;c. v.</HI> 44. if Ori∣ginal sin was not here intended? What but their way of understanding it indu∣ced
<PB N="7" REF="9"/>
the Heathen Philosophers, some to extol Nature as a noble Mother, and simply vertuous, some to depress her as an obscure step-dame, and absolutely vi∣tious: Some to lament at the immerited evils of birth; some to laugh that it should be thought a man could be born with any vice or crime about him? for this was part of that which unto the Greeks seemed foolishness, 1 <HI>Corinth.</HI> 1. 23. That one should be saved by a∣nother mans merits, that one should be just with another mans righteousness, that one should suffer and satisfie for a∣nother mans offences, and that one should be accounted wicked for another mans sins; And in very deed, the Greeks seeking after wisdom, or men curiously Philosophizing and labouring in the Ob∣jections and answers of natural reason, hath been the main thing that hath in∣vented and maintained all the opinions and errors about Original sin; Neither in truth is this natural reasoning of men any other than every mans own way of understanding it. But let us goe on to take further notice of what notorious errors (or heresies rather) that have been not only broached but stifly main∣tained
<PB N="8" REF="10"/>
thereby (<HI>scilicet</HI>) that Original sin, name, and thing, is nothing. That no sin from <HI>Adam</HI> passes upon Men ei∣ther at their conception, or at their birth, neither so much as imputed to po∣sterity, that <HI>Adams</HI> sin hurt none but himself, and that Infants are born in the same state <HI>Adam</HI> was in before his praevarication. That no man is lyable to damnation because of <HI>Adams</HI> sin. That <HI>Adams</HI> sin passes no other way upon his Posterity but by example or imitation only: That Original sin is not remitted to Infants by Baptism, because there is no such thing in them; so the <HI>Pelagians,</HI> and <HI>Coelestians.</HI> That sins (both O∣riginal and actual) were created by an evil Principle, that is an evil God. That no sin is caused by Free will, but by the evil Principle aforesaid, That sin is the very nature and substance of Man. That some were so born in sin that Christ could not save them; so the <HI>Ma∣nichees.</HI> That Original sin is in no sort to be ascribed unto Man, but either to God, or else to the Devil; so the <HI>Her∣mogenians,</HI> and <HI>Valentinians.</HI> That O∣riginal sin is the least of all sins: That it is in the Body, and not in the Soul,
<PB N="9" REF="10"/>
or that it is in the inferiour faculties of the Soul only, and not in the superiour. That Original sin is called sin <HI>equivocally, abusively, figuratively,</HI> or by a <HI>Meto∣nymie,</HI> either as the Cause of sin, or as caused by sin. That after Baptism it is no real viciosity, but only a penalty. That the whole, and all of it, is not on∣ly not imputed, and remitted, but quite taken away and blotted out by Baptism. That Concupiscence remaining in the re∣generate is no sin. That there is no Law against the loss of Original righteous∣ness. That notwithstanding the worst of Original sin, there will remain in us much both moral, civil, pious, and Spiri∣tual good. That it is only a guilt bind∣ing over to punishment, but no fault of sin properly defiling, so the <HI>Pontificians,</HI> and especially their <HI>Scholasticks.</HI> That it is neither defection, depravation, cor∣ruption, nor truly and properly a Sin, but only an affliction or punishment de∣scending upon posterity through the guilt of <HI>Adams transgression,</HI> like as to be born a Slave or a Bastard is his shame only, and not his sin. That nothing was born in us, and with us which was not good, and the very work of God. That
<PB N="10" REF="11"/>
<HI>Adams</HI> disobedience was in no wise ours, neither were we therefore in any wise obnoxious to eternal death; so the <HI>Pig∣hians</HI> and the <HI>Catharinians.</HI> That we become infected by Original sin, not by way of Generation or Propagation, but only by way of imitation and out∣ward occasion. That the death of the body is the sequel of Nature, and no pu∣nishment for sin whether original or a∣ctual; so the <HI>Socinians</HI> and <HI>Racovians.</HI> That Original sin is not a vicious acci∣dent or adjunct, but is become our very Nature, Essence, and Substance; the ve∣ry heart, and flesh, and body, and soul; so the <HI>Flaccians,</HI> and <HI>Substantialists.</HI> That a mans meer pure naturals (not∣withstanding the <HI>Fall</HI>) are good and perfect. That Original sin is but like a little spot upon the skin, or light wound, for all which there remain still in a man his natural capacities, dispositions, pow∣ers, and forces to Good. That Men from their Mothers womb, are as fully endowed with <HI>Liberty</HI> and <HI>Freewill,</HI> as <HI>Adam</HI> was before his <HI>fall.</HI> That <HI>Origi∣nal sin</HI> to a man's <HI>Freewill,</HI> is but like <HI>Garlick</HI> to a <HI>Loadstone,</HI> easily wipt off, and so it falls to work as fresh as at the
<PB N="11" REF="11"/>
first. That the <HI>Adamical</HI> will, or will from <HI>Adams</HI> fall, hath it self not merely passive in the act of <HI>Conversion</HI>; but is thereunto actively cooperating together with God; so the <HI>Erasmians,</HI> the <HI>Su∣nergicts,</HI> and <HI>Arminians.</HI> That Origi∣nal sin was but St. <HI>Augustins dream</HI> and <HI>Puppet.</HI> That Infants under the <HI>New Testament</HI> are not born in Original sin. That there's no necessity to baptize In∣fants, with respect to any benefit they thus can have against it. That Original sin and all other is to be remedied only by <HI>revelations</HI> and <HI>raptures</HI> of the Spirit, without any use either of <HI>Word</HI> or <HI>Sacra∣ments</HI>; so the <HI>Swenckfeldians,</HI> the <HI>En∣thousiasts, Anabaptists, Fanaticks,</HI> and <HI>Familists.</HI> That Original sin is not pro∣perly a <HI>sin,</HI> but a <HI>Disease,</HI> or a <HI>Condition,</HI> or else figurative form of speaking (<HI>viz.</HI> by a <HI>Metonymie</HI>) may be so called; so <HI>Zwinglius,</HI> and some of the <HI>Zwinglians.</HI> That God reprobates, God damns men absolutely because it is his will and plea∣sure, without any respect or condition whether of Original or Actual sin; so the <HI>Supralapsarians.</HI> Thus you see, Sir, what a crowd of Errors have obtruded only through mens leaning to their
<PB N="12" REF="12"/>
own understandings, amongst which, more than once, this Author may find his own, which to me (at first view) seems so like to diverse of the aforesaid Errors, that taken up in strict syllables, I begin to suspect it would not only ap∣pear so, but appear so, and much more. But I look not upon him in a likenesse to them, but in some unlikenesse to the <HI>Holy Scriptures,</HI> and the <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI> taking his way of understanding it to be another, both to what the first teaches to understand, and in what the last would be understood. And let him not think I speak this as one that would revile him, but as one that (accor∣ding to his understanding) must dis∣sent from him, using my <HI>liberty</HI> (which I wish may be mutual) but keeping my <HI>Charity</HI> nevertheless; my understanding I doe faithfully, and in all humility sub∣mit to those two witnesses, neither will I oppose him in any thing but what I re∣ceive from them (they that will under∣take him in other passages, that fall not directly within this compass, let them do it as they shall find themselves concern∣ed in it, or called to it.) This I take to be the safest way to begin, and (if he
<PB N="13" REF="12"/>
will keep his own word) the readiest way to make an end. For taking the 5 Chapter to the <HI>Romans</HI> to be objected a∣gainst him; <HI>If it be so</HI> (saies he) <HI>I have done,</HI> if it be not so (say I) I have no∣thing to do. Let me be beleeved both by him and you in this: I have look'd again and again upon his Paraphrase with a single eye, only to find out truth, and proper truth, if there explained, hoping he will doe likewise with this <HI>Exposition,</HI> when it shall come to his sight; <HI>In which</HI> (I make his own words mine) <HI>if I use any violence I can easily be reproved.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="section">
<PB N="14" REF="13"/>
<HEAD>For the Scripture.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Rom. 5. 12.</BIBL>
<Q>Wherefore as by one Man Sin entred into the World, and Death by Sin, and so Death passed up∣on all Men, for that all have sin∣ned.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Wherefore, there∣fore, for this cause</HI>] I begin with the search and examination of the letter, for it is the Grammatical sifting, that must render the plain Constructi∣on, and then the <HI>Rhetorical glossing</HI> may come in to adorn with a certain circum∣locution; and therefore a broad <HI>Para∣phrase</HI> if it be not unsuitable, yet it is untimely, when it shall presume in place, before a narrower <HI>Exposition</HI> have done its part. <HI>For this canse,</HI> so I am bold to render it, because I find it most∣ly so rendred in this Epistle to the <HI>Ro∣mans,</HI>
<PB N="15" REF="13"/>
chap. 1. 26. and 13. 6. and 15. 9. which very inference serves to shew plainly the principal reason or cause why it pleased God to permit the <HI>Entrance</HI> and <HI>Passage</HI> of Original Sin, <HI>viz. For this cause,</HI> even for the <HI>reconciliation</HI> and <HI>attonements</HI> sake immediately be∣fore spoken of, <HI>vers</HI>: 10. and 11. There∣fore God suffered this sin to enter into the world, The <HI>Enmity,</HI> or hainous a∣version, the wrath or dreadfull desert of Original Sin can never be more truly and fully considered and measured than in and by <HI>Christs death</HI> and <HI>satisfaction,</HI> which who so contends to lessen either for <HI>Fault</HI> or <HI>Guilt,</HI> such endeavours to extenuate the vertue and merits of <HI>Christs reconciling</HI> and <HI>attoning.</HI> Gods great end in the <HI>Fall</HI> was to manifest and magnifie the infinite perfection of his own <HI>Son</HI>; who then would not la∣bour earnestly, that Wisdom might principally, be justified in the point? Doth not God herein commend his love towards us, <HI>vers.</HI> 8. How then can we imagin there should be the least prejudice upon the Divine Attri∣butes in such an Ordination or Permissi∣on, upon such a motive or intention?
<PB N="16" REF="14"/>
But was this inferential motive heedlesly escaped or not rather purposely preter∣mitted to usurp a more uncontrouled li∣cence in the wanton daliances of words, that I may not call them petulancies of prophanation? <HI>It is no reputation to a Phisician to say he hath cured us of an E∣vil which we never had, and shall we ac∣cuse the Father of mercies to have wound∣ed us for no other reason, but that his Son may have the honour to have cured us? I understand not that; he that makes a ne∣cessity that he may find a remedy, is like,</HI> &amp;c. The sufficiency and excellency of our Saviour (in this case) is a thing that both he and we all are bound to under∣stand and seriously beleeve, and not on∣ly that, but Gods ordination and dis∣pensation to such an end, as the manife∣station of his honour and glory: But why such playing with a thing so sacred? As here's nothing to provoke his spleen to indignation, from an horrible decree of absolute necessitating and damning; so neither can I see any thing that should move it to laughter or levity; the Apostle himself defines what af∣fection it is that should hence be raised, <HI>We joy in God through our Lord Iesus
<PB N="17" REF="14"/>
Christ, ver.</HI> 11. and well we may, since the sufferance or entrance of Sin is here referred to the gracious purpose of <HI>Re∣conciling, attoning,</HI> and <HI>saving.</HI> Is this the way of vindicating the glory of the Divine Attributes, to make no more but a light jest at Christs honour in this kind? still I say <HI>Wisdom is justified of all her Children, Luk.</HI> 7. 34, 39. this he himself spake when men imputed to him a carnal Dispensation with our actual Sins; and so much may we say when a∣ny man will deprive him of that honour is due unto him from his spiritual dis∣pensation in our Originals. Neither let him say to us, <HI>That the honour of our bles∣sed Saviour does no way depend upon our imaginations, and weak Propositions,</HI> we will say so too, and peradventure might say so more justly against him; only we let him know right inferences are no imagi∣nations, neither are strong deductions weak propositions. And if what I have drawn hence be not directly from the Text, let him but be pleased to take the illative along with him, and then inferr what he can otherwise, or to the con∣trary. I confess I would not in any wise have this illation thought <HI>redun∣dant,</HI>
<PB N="18" REF="15"/>
for that were to make the <HI>Scripture</HI> either impure and corrupt, or or else idle and superfluous; yet should I not have excepted at all, if any (fol∣lowing my <HI>Siriack</HI> Transletion) had o∣mitted it upon this consideration; That it is a hard matter (especially in a com∣parison betwixt <HI>Adam</HI> and <HI>Christ</HI>) to define a cause, or give a reason for O∣riginal Sins entrance into the world, or descent upon posterity. But then this should be observed withall, if such a thing be hardly rendred, it should not be rashly inquired into, because our <HI>in∣quisitiveness</HI> (in this case) tends more to the dishonour, than all our <HI>Resolution</HI> can to the honour of the <HI>Divine Attri∣butes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>As by one Man</HI>] Whom we may (not amiss) understand in an unity of name, order, person, nature, sex, action, and Type. 1. Of name, <HI>Adam,</HI> which ap∣pellation comprehends also both the person, the sex, and the kind. 2. Of Or∣der, <HI>sc.</HI> the first man <HI>Adam.</HI> 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15. 45. and so the very <HI>Hebraism,</HI> or <HI>Grecism</HI> (of the cardinal for the ordinal) would give it if need were. 3. Of <HI>Person, sc.</HI> in the individual, in number singularly
<PB N="19" REF="15"/>
and precisely taken, and so Original Sin properly derived from the prime, and not from the proximate Parents, or according to their pluralities, 4. Of sex, the male and not the female, who though she was first in the transgres∣sion, yet some will have him to be sole∣ly understood in this propagation. But, for my part, I confesse I can see no cause for such an exception, but that they may be understood one <HI>Flesh,</HI> one in the <HI>Image,</HI> one in the <HI>praevarication,</HI> and so one in the <HI>Propagation.</HI> 5. Of <HI>Nature,</HI> as one not only <HI>in individuo</HI> but <HI>in specie,</HI> one comprehending and re∣presenting the whole root and stock and seed and generation, and nature and con∣dition of Mankind, so <HI>Adam</HI> is taken for the whole <HI>species</HI> of Men, and the <HI>Beast</HI> singularly for the whole species of Beasts. 6. Of <HI>Act,</HI> namely, one in the <HI>Dis-obedience</HI> or <HI>Offence.</HI> For it was not the simple or meer nature that was the means of such a derivation, but the of∣fending and disobedient Nature, by which (causally and instrumentally) this privation and depravatiou, this stain and guilt descended upon all; yea not only the <HI>Offence of one,</HI> but one of∣fence;
<PB N="20" REF="16"/>
for it was his first Act that was imputed to us, and none of the rest. 7. Of <HI>Type,</HI> for <HI>Adam</HI> is here said to be the <HI>Figure</HI> or <HI>Type</HI> of <HI>Christ,</HI> under this no∣tion (<HI>of one</HI>) as much as in any thing else, he whole Comparison throughout.</P>
<P><HI>Sin</HI>] No great matter how many and various soever be the acceptions of Sin in the <HI>Scriptures,</HI> since in this place it is defined by the Apostle to be Sin in the singular, and not said plurally Sins, as if he would precisely determine it of that one root of Sin, distinct from those many following fruits. Yea, it may be thus rendred <HI>the Sin,</HI> very Emphatically, and is understood by almost all (from antient to modern) for no other but O∣riginal Sin simply so accepted, as the only Sin which came by <HI>one Man</HI> singu∣larly, and <HI>entred into all the world</HI> uni∣versally, whereas actual sins are by ma∣ny men, neither enter they into all the world in general, but rather into these and those particulars therein; yea it is Sin simply, absolutely, properly, formally: For (as himself grants) this Sin had its beginning <HI>by the disobedience of Adam,</HI> and disobedience is a transgression of a Law, and that's the very formality of
<PB N="21" REF="16"/>
Sin; and that law was the law of the I∣mage, or of perfect Nature. Now see Sir I beseech you! what is here (but in the least shew) whereby to collect this sin to be <HI>Metonymically</HI> so called? or what kind of <HI>Metonymie</HI> would he have it? is it a <HI>Metonymie</HI> of the cause put for the effect? So it seems he would have it, <HI>because it is the effect of one sin</HI>: Surely that <HI>one sin</HI> was a proper and real cause; how strange is it then, That it should beget an effect like to it in no thing, but in a Tropical or Trala∣titious, an equivocal and abusive name? if by the cause for the effect be meant Sin but for the Punishment, how contrary is that to St. <HI>Pauls</HI> express words. <HI>Sin entred into the world, and death by Sin,</HI> so far is he from confounding them, that in most express manner he distinguishes between them, both in name and signifi∣cation; For should his words be made to signifie thus, <HI>Death,</HI> (that is the <HI>punish∣ment</HI>) entered by Sin (that is the pu∣nishment) <HI>Death</HI> the punishment of the punishment, I beseech you what sense were this? yet we grant (though it is not so to be argued from the word in this place) Original Sin is both a Sin and
<PB N="22" REF="17"/>
a punishment too: A sin, from the hu∣mane injustice perverting, a punish∣ment, from the Divine Justice deserting: Or will he have it a <HI>Metonymie</HI> of the Effect put for the Cause? for so his o∣ther words intimate, <HI>because it is the cause of many sins,</HI> and those many sins, (without doubt) he means properly so called; then seems it so much the more strange, and almost prodigious, that so many real effects should proceed from a poorly equivocal and transnominated cause. <HI>Rhetoricians</HI> observe that such kind of <HI>Metonymies</HI> are usual in exter∣nal causes and effects only: that an in∣ternal cause then should be put for an external effect must needs be most unu∣sual.</P>
<P><HI>Entred into the World.</HI>] We may un∣derstand this Entrance of Sin in divers senses, and that very <HI>Orthodoxally.</HI> 1. Sin was not in the beginning: for it had no being before the <HI>Entring,</HI> and there∣fore was no eternal evil principle, but only the issue of some inordinate and ir∣regular Act. 2. <HI>It entered</HI> not as a creature or substance that had some exi∣stence in it self, but as a vicious accident that could not subsist without a Subject,
<PB N="23" REF="17"/>
in which it must inhere: And therefore though it entred into our Nature and substance, yet our nature and Substance it was not. 3. <HI>It entered not of it self,</HI> but by means, by one man, by a second cause. Therefore (himself grants) Sin had its beginning, and thence let the fault and guilt be fetcht causally, what need is there to seek further than the beginning? why then is there such prying into the first cause? such disputing, such labour∣ing to entitle hereunto his Decreeing, his ordaining, and permitting, disposing, dispensing, &amp;c. For so indeed the most we do is bus to disparage and dishonour him in his glorious Titles and Attri∣but. It is enough for us to beleeve him to be just, wise, good, &amp;c. in all things, because he cannot possibly be otherwise, although in some dispensations it is not possible for us to comprehend him. 4: <HI>If entred into,</HI> Loe! the <HI>Apostle</HI> speaks plainly of an ingression, not as of an accession of a thing inward, and not out∣ward only, doubtless then it must needs be something <HI>inherent</HI> and not <HI>imputed only.</HI> 5. <HI>It entred into the World <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> it came into,</HI> even the reduplicated praeposition is a note of more intimate
<PB N="24" REF="18"/>
and peculiar manner of introduction, namely by way of Generation and Pro∣pagation, not by <HI>Temptation</HI> nor by <HI>I∣mitation</HI>; not by <HI>Temptation,</HI> for so it came from the <HI>Devil</HI> to <HI>Eve</HI>; not by <HI>Imitation,</HI> for so it came from <HI>Eve</HI> to <HI>A∣dam</HI>; but by Propagation, for so it came from <HI>Adam to us all.</HI> Had it been otherwise than so, Sin could not (in any adaptness or propriety) have been said to have <HI>Entred into the world</HI>; but the world must then have caused it, and called it, and sought it, and brought it, and taught it to it self.</P>
<P><HI>And death by Sin</HI>] that is to say, by the same Sin which came into the world by one Man, namely the Original: So then death it is, that cannot be denied: But now men must be Judges, and take upon them to determine what kind of death, albeit the <HI>Apostle</HI> speak it never so indefinitely. <HI>He must mean temporal death,</HI> says he; well and thus he may inferr it, because St. <HI>Paul</HI> speaks of such a Death as entred into this world, and that's but temporal: But then he ought to observe withall, that St. <HI>Paul</HI> speaks here, not only of Deaths first Entrance, but of Deaths through passage; now
<PB N="25" REF="18"/>
such a passage is out of the world, and beyond it, and so must be eternal. But he objects, <HI>eternal death did not pass upon all men.</HI> That's easie to be answe∣red from some of his own words. The <HI>Sentence</HI> did, though the <HI>Execution</HI> did not; in the one was the Divine Justice to be magnified, and his Mercy in the o∣ther. Thus the Divine Attributes know how to save, and to exalt themselves on either side: if men would not seek to make them seem to clash, by hum∣bling those high things to their low and weak apprehensions.</P>
<P><HI>And so Death passed upon all men</HI>] <HI>sc.</HI> Death entred by Sin; and so (by Sin) Death passed: So that (whether we consider the <HI>terminus a quo,</HI> or <HI>ad quem</HI>) we may directly hence collect, that Death (even the coporal as well as the eternal) was not the sequel or necessity of Nature, but even the penalty and wa∣ges of Sin, because death is a separation quite contrary to the natural union, e∣specially to that of Nature in her inte∣grity and original perfection. But say that (because of a composition, and that of contrary Elements) there might be nevertheless some kind of <HI>mutation, mi∣gration,
<PB N="26" REF="19"/>
melioration</HI>; yet this was far from <HI>separation, dissolution, confusion,</HI> and that dolorous and ignominious, execra∣ble and damnable. This makes me I cannot so well brook or digest those pas∣sages of his. <HI>His Sin left him to his Na∣ture,—we returned to the state of meer na∣ture — of our prime creation — thrust back to the form of Nature — was remanded to his mortal natural State,</HI> — means he to a corrupt state of Nature? that was not the former, or from the prime Cre∣ation; or means he by the form of Na∣ture that of Natures first forming? why that was after the Divine Image and si∣militude; or means he by meer Nature those they call <HI>Pure Naturals?</HI> which indeed are nothing, because Nature can∣not be so abstractly considered, but ei∣ther in the state of Integrity, or in the state of Corruption, a third state (be∣fore, between, of after those two) never was, and therefore is not to be imagi∣ned. Ever since the Fall, and Origi∣nal Sin we aptly conceive that there is a difference still to be made betwixt the substance of Nature, and the corruption of Nature: But that this Nature and this corruption was ever separated in any
<PB N="27" REF="19"/>
(Christ only excepted) we beleeve not, or that there shall be a State of pure Na∣turals again till the Resurrection of the Dead. We all know and beleeve <HI>Adam</HI> by his disobedience defected and fell from what he was before, <HI>sc.</HI> from the Image and Original Righteousness, but that by his Sin he fell into a Nature or state which he had before, or without original righteousness, that we under∣stand not, not yet of any remanding, obtruding or returning thither. Indeed we read, God said, <HI>Dust thou art, and to Dust thou shalt return, Gen.</HI> 3. 19. but that noted only some materials in part, but no certain state, neither had that dust returned to the dust, but that the Image and righteousness was forfeited and lost. For we see it was so not by a natural propensity, so much as by a pro∣voked Commination. Besides this, me∣thinks he says something to oppose him∣self in this part, when he says, <HI>our Na∣ture is of Gods making,</HI> and <HI>consequently is good,</HI> — or <HI>Nature is almost the same,</HI> &amp;c.— What good? and yet punished? nay and we remanded to it for a punish∣ment? What almost the same in good∣ness? and yet nothing the same in im∣mortality and the blessing? Thus here
<PB N="28" REF="20"/>
again Gods Justice is brought upon the Stage; nay and upon the rack too, espe∣cially by our scanning betwixt the two Terms of <HI>Death entring by one man,</HI> and <HI>Death passing upon all men.</HI>— For we cry, why the punishment, and how, of all, for one, &amp; so forth? Mean while it is not considered by us (Nay not believed) how we were all in the lump &amp; loyns of that one, which remains hereafter to be de∣monstrated, only thus much is now to be said, That while the Divine Attributes are pretended for, saved harmless by us, either we our selves doe it, or else give occasion for others to quarrel at them.</P>
<P><HI>For that all have sinned</HI>] This clause thus translated was greedily snatch'd at of old, to extenuate and excuse the severi∣ty of Deaths universal passing; and not only so, but to alter and divert the cause and guilt, from the Original Sin to the Actual. For this cause the Antients did either reject this Translation, or did not so wel accept it: But I am to speak of this our Paraphrast, whose words (by reason of this Translation) are imposing on the Apostle, <HI>if he means eternal Death,</HI> he must not mean that it came for <HI>Adams</HI> sin, <HI>but in as much as all men have sin∣ned,</HI> that is, upon all those upon whom
<PB N="29" REF="20"/>
eternal death did come, <HI>it came because they also have sinned</HI>; and again in pas∣sing on us, <HI>For that all have sinned, that is, the sin was reckoned to all, not to make them guilty like</HI> Adam, <HI>but</HI> Adams <HI>Sin pas'd upon all imprinting this real calamity on us all; but yet death descended also upon</HI> A∣dam's <HI>posterity for their own Sins, for since all did Sin all should die.</HI> His (<HI>also</HI>) once and again seems to admit of original sin for her share in this reckoning; but his (<HI>in asmuch</HI>) quite thrusts it out, &amp; brings in actual sin in its stead; Actual sin I say is obtruded and Original sin excluded; at least for propriety, for guilt, for imputati∣on, for likeness, for equality: Yet I shall not therefore reject this Translation, be∣cause I see our Church hath accepted it, and shall hope to make it stand good in this sense, <HI>For that all have sinned,</HI> that is, sinned Originally although not Actu∣ally, sinned naturally in <HI>Adams</HI> Sin, al∣though as yet not personally, or in their own, and am confident he is not igno∣rant I can find Abettors for this exposi∣tion amongst the reformed and Ortho∣dox Expositors far before him: But, Sir, if you will be pleased to look upon the Margin (which I suppose he winked at)
<PB N="30" REF="21"/>
know it is pointed at by our Church as a note of equal indifferency and authority, and there you find <HI>in whom all have sin∣ned,</HI> this speaks plainly of sinning not actually in our selves, but originally in <HI>Adam</HI>; and this Translation is every whit as much, and rather more congru∣ous to the <HI>Original Text</HI>: for my part I rather embrace this latter Translation, with most Translaters or Interpreters old or late. And with them conceive it to be the safer, as not giving such way to the Errors of the <HI>Pelagians</HI> old or new: Nay I hold it to be the sounder, and more consonant to the very Letter; for why should (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) be translated so flatly in the Neuter Gender, when 'tis found so Emphatically in the Masculine? being it may with so close and so apt Concotd be referred to the <HI>One Man</HI> spoken of before; for construe it in the Masculine, and the Relative fairly agrees with the proximate and eminent Ante∣cedent; but take it in the Neuter, and then the Relative is without any Antece∣dent at all, or else must be turned into some obscurer and less significant part of speech. <HI>Erasmus</HI> (who labours like a Critick to draw it this other way) would
<PB N="31" REF="21"/>
not allow of St. <HI>Augustines</HI> referring it to Sin; because of the different gender, though he confesses it to be the same in sense to say, in which Man, or in which Sin. As for <HI>Erasmus,</HI> (whom all have occasion to honour, from the Cradle to the Crown of learning) him this Author recommends to us more precisely to be reckoned amongst the greatest <HI>and the best Expositors of Scripture that any age</HI> since the <HI>Apostles, and their immediate Successors hath brought forth</HI>; (as for the learned <HI>Grotius,</HI> whom he reckons with him, I only say thus much; As he was a most eminent Adversary to the <HI>So∣cinian,</HI> so he was sometimes a not appro∣ved Advocate of the <HI>Arminian,</HI> both which are reproved for their opinions a∣bout Original sin) But on Gods name let him add all he can to <HI>Erasmus,</HI> yet I would not have him detract any thing from St. <HI>Augustin</HI> (which thing was sometime charged upon <HI>Erasmus</HI> him∣self) both are to be mentioned with ho∣nour as the <HI>Worthies</HI> of their <HI>Ages.</HI> And therefore all he hath said (had it been more) should have past for me without exception, had he spoken it at another time, and upon another place: For up∣on
<PB N="32" REF="22"/>
on this place (he cannot but know) That <HI>Erasmus</HI> hath not only been suspected but taxed (even by learned men of his own time and religion) for more than I now think fit to express: only as to the clause, nay and whole verse in hand <HI>Erasmus</HI> is much contend∣ing for a Tropologie (and peradventure hence it was that he hinted his <HI>Metony∣mie</HI>) But for all his Rhetorick he turns Grammarian, and plaies the Critick be∣twixt, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> and <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> and will hardly be perswaded of <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> for <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in the Dative Case, yet at length acknowledges, <HI>Be∣cause the use of Greek Prepositions are so various, I dare not affirm that <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> is no where joyned with a Dative Case, where one thing is declared to be in another, like as the Tree is in the seed.</HI> A most apt si∣militude to illustrate our being in <HI>Adam,</HI> and our sinning in him too. Were it not for this his confession, places of such construction were easie to be produced, but I spare them, as likewise his <HI>propter unum,</HI> his <HI>pervasit,</HI> his <HI>quatenus peccavi∣mus,</HI> which also might be of a facile con∣nivence, were it not in case of dangerous consequence and contention; besides my task is to pursue, not his but this Authors paraphrase.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="33" REF="22"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 13.</BIBL>
<Q>For until the Law Sin was in the World, but sin is not imputed where there is no Law.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>FOr until the Law Sin was in the world</HI>] That is, from the beginning, of the world, all that time which went before, until that very period wherein the Law was externally promulgated: Sin was ne∣vertheless (even all that while) in the world: For the <HI>Apostle</HI> so speaks now, with intent to occur to a certain objecti∣on, (an Objection not so much of mens <HI>Mervail</HI> or <HI>Scruple,</HI> but rather of their <HI>Petulancy</HI> and <HI>Cavillation</HI>) an objection that indeed hath been always but too much inculcated by the <HI>Adversaries</HI> of Original Sin: Thus, Where there is no <HI>Law,</HI> there is no transgression: But there is no Law given against Original Sin. <HI>Ergo.</HI> This is it which the Apo∣stle here prevents, by saying. <HI>Sin</HI> was in the world during all that space of time which went before the giving or promul∣ging of the Law of <HI>Moses,</HI> notwith∣standing it was not a Sin without a Law, but so it was by vertue of the Law of Na∣ture;
<PB N="34" REF="23"/>
the rule of original righteousness, the dictates of right reason, the eternal moral Law; the Law written in <HI>Mens hearts,</HI> before it was written in <HI>Tables</HI> of <HI>stone</HI>: For Original sin was not so much forbidden, convinced, condemn∣ed by the promulgated Law that follow∣ed it, and was directed chiefly to per∣sons and actions: as by the internal law of the Image which went before it, with a perpetual obligation of integrity to the whole Nature; of such a Law speaks the Apostle in this Epistle, <HI>When the Gen∣tiles which have not the Law do by Na∣ture the things contained in the Law, these having not the Law, are a Law unto themselves, which shew the work of the Law written in their hearts, their con∣science also bearing witness, and their thoughts the mean while accusing or else excusing one another.</HI> Rom. 2. 14, 15. And this certainly was Law sufficient both to convince men of this Sin, and condemn them for it. Say the Law of Nature be greatly obscured, and the conscience thereupon blinded; yet for all that it is usually making this ar∣gument, upon any pecrancy: Some∣thing now is which ought not to be, and
<PB N="35" REF="23"/>
therefore by consequence, something is not which ought to be, and thus by the exorbitances grows conscious of the de∣fects, and this Collection is enough for conviction of the want of natural good∣ness, and that is a divine apprehension of the loss of original righteousness, wherefore then speaks he thus? <HI>Nature a∣lone gives rules, but does not bind to penal∣ties</HI>;—if by Nature alone he means fallen, corrupted nature, now in her defections, she gives neither rules, nor binds to pe∣nalties; but only lies bound both to rules and to penalties. But to speak of Na∣ture in her integrity and perfection, she doth them both directly, for she were not perfect without a rule, neither were her rule perfect without a penalty upon the violation of it; his other words (in my judgement) as they are little to the <HI>Apostles</HI> meaning, so they are lesse to common Truth, <HI>Death</HI> (he says) <HI>d<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d presently descend upon all Mankind even before a Law was given them, with an appendant penalty,</HI> viz. <HI>with the express intermination of death</HI>; was not that Law exprest enough? <HI>In that day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die.</HI> Gen. 2. 17, I need not ask him whether this
<PB N="36" REF="24"/>
Law did concern the man alone? for he confesses it did presently descend upon all Mankind; But what? death without a Law? and a Law without a penalty? He that contended so before to vindi∣cate Gods attributes in regard of a <HI>Sen∣tence</HI> without <HI>Execution,</HI> how will he extricate himself from impinging there∣upon, in talking thus of an <HI>Execution</HI> without a <HI>Sentence</HI>? certainly the Di∣vine Attributes are much more out of question, in pronouncing utterly upon all, and yet sparing some, than in exe∣cuting upon all (although but in the least degree) having not yet denounced against any. As for his next words, let him look well to what he saies, it is im∣possible they should passe even mode∣rate men without a censure, or some scanning at the least; <HI>with him,</HI> (that is with <HI>Adam</HI>) <HI>God being angry</HI> (was he provoked against the person only, and not against the whole Nature) <HI>was pleas∣ed to curse</HI> (was not that pleasure in a manner absolute, that had no more but an improper respect to curse all for the Sin of one?) <HI>To curse him also in his posterity</HI> (nay was it not rather to curse his posterity in him? for he but little
<PB N="37" REF="24"/>
felt his curse in them, but they were long to feel their curse in him?) <HI>and leave them also in their meer natural con∣dition</HI> (was this natural condition any kind of state before the <HI>Fall?</HI> then could it not be cursed or miserable; was it that after the Fall? then was it not meer or pure natural, but altogether de∣praved and corrupted) <HI>But God was pleased to leave them</HI>: (So then Gods great and easily justifiable action, was the good pleasure of his desertion, wise∣ly, justly to leave them destitute of the forfeited Image, and to let them alone to themselves in that corrupt condition to which they betrayed:) But he says more, <HI>To which yet they disposed them∣selves.</HI> To what? to their meer natural condition, to which God curst them, in which he left them. But how dispo∣sed themselves hereunto? I hope he will not say 'twas any personal disposition of ours, for that goes far beyond all that hath been said of our natural inclination; but if he intend it only of our actnal and following sins, they did not dispose us to our fall'n estate, and corrupt natural condition; but only confirm us in it; what can be spoken more against Order
<PB N="38" REF="25"/>
than that following actions should dis∣pose to a foregoing condition? we use to say, the first person corrupted our Nature; but in all else it is the nature that corrupts the persons; personal sins are no whit disposing to the Nature, but aggravating to the person only: <HI>Original Sin,</HI> though it doe not act alike in all, yet it is but one and alike in all, be the personal actions more or less. He concludes, <HI>yet for the anger which God had against Mankind he left that Death which he threatned to</HI> Adam <HI>expresly by implication to fall upon his posterity.</HI> Now I demand but this, Was the anger of God with <HI>Adam,</HI> and against <HI>Mankind,</HI> the same? well then it had the same pro∣vocation: Nay, but he will have this last to be upon our own evil <HI>Commissions</HI> and <HI>deserts</HI>; Then I must demand again why was that Death the same? is it righteous that should be the same penal∣ty, and not the same provocation? But he left it to fall by <HI>Implication,</HI> that's an implicated word, and may imply Error, as well as truth: If he implies our Original defection, that's a truth; but if our actual Commissions only, that's the Error: But I will take (by implica∣tion) as he here contradistinguishes it to
<PB N="39" REF="25"/>
<HI>Expressively threatned,</HI> and so it draws near, nay comes home to the truth of my Text: That before <HI>Moses Law</HI> sin was in the world, even Original Sin, and the Sin of the first Parent, and that by a Law of its own, which Law though it was <HI>Expressively threatned</HI> but to <HI>Adam</HI> only, yet by <HI>implication</HI> (of Sin and cor∣ruption in the whole nature) the punish∣ment (through that implying Law) just∣ly fell upon the whole <HI>posterity.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But Sin is not imputed where there is no Law.</HI>] In these words St. <HI>Pauls</HI> in∣tention is not so much to prove the be∣ing of Sin, from the being of a Law; but rather the being of a Law, from the being of a Sin: And therefore he thus argues, Sin was in the world before the promulgation of <HI>Moses Law</HI>: but that could not be unless there was a Law to convince it so to be. <HI>Ergo</HI> A law there was. And again Sin is not imputed when there is no Law; but it was imputed. <HI>Ergo</HI> there was a Law. And this is the more certain and infallible way of argu∣ing, because the being of a Law does not necessarily, and always argue the being of a Sin, but the being of a Sin does ne∣cessarily and always argue the being of
<PB N="40" REF="26"/>
a Law; For a Law may be a Law, though no sin be yet committed: but a Sin is no Sin till the Law be imposed; now the Law was always, as being the eternal Law, and eternally existing in the divine mind, yea, and more or less imprinted in the minds and consciences of Men from the beginning. The Law therefore being before the Sin, there was no time of the world after Sin, wherein Sin was not imputed. But much adoe is here made by the means of di∣stinguishing or diversifying Questions, <HI>viz.</HI> whether this imputing of Sin be by God, or by men? whether it be of Ori∣ginal Sin, or of actual? whether it be by the eternal and natural, or by the written and published Law; whether it be of the fault and corruption, or of the guilt and punishment, whether it be to penalty temporal or eternal? whether this imputation be of our own sins or a∣nothers? Whether this imputation be distinguished or divided from inherence? Thus we trouble our selves and one ano∣ther, and the Truth betwixt us with many a Fallacy of Division; whereas much error were to be avoided by taking both together in a conjoyned sense, and
<PB N="41" REF="26"/>
the Truth were easily determined in all those questions, or in most part of any of the questions; by accepting both parts indifferently, even the one as well as the other. As to speak only to this Authors words or divided Propositions: <HI>The Apostle</HI> (he saith) <HI>speaketh here of Sin imputed; therefore not of Sin inhe∣rent.</HI> Not so by his leave, for the Apo∣stle speaks not here of any distinction at all, betwixt imputed and inherent sin; but of Sin indefinitely and universally, and that imputed only by a Law; now the Law properly imputes Sin, be it ne∣ver so properly inherent, as in actual sins, though they be inherent; yet the Law properly does but impute them: So in Original Sin, the Law does im∣pute it, yet so as it is inherent. So that in one or other the Sin is nevertheless in∣herent for being imputed; nor imputed for being inherent: <HI>And if imputed to such purposes as he here speaks of,</HI> viz. <HI>to Temporal Death: then it is neither a Sin properly, nor yet imputable so eternal; so far as is or can be implyed by the Apostles words.</HI> Yes, yes, the contrary to all his in every purpose is not only implyed, but apparent from the <HI>Apostles</HI> words.
<PB N="42" REF="27"/>
For the <HI>Apostle</HI> speaks of Death indefi∣nitely (without any limitation to these or those purposes) and that's an univer∣sal implying all kinds of Death: Besides Death here by <HI>Adam</HI> must so be taken as proportionably extending to the-life by Christ; otherwise wrong is done to the whole comparison, and consequent∣ly to all our <HI>Saviours Attributes</HI>; Now the life we are here said to gain by the Excellency of Christ, is not only a cor∣poral life, opposite to a temporal death, but a justification of life, opposite to a spiritual Death, and a reigning in life, opposite to an eternal Death: <HI>Whensoe∣ver another mans sin is imputed to his re∣lative, therefore, becaeuse it is anothers, and imputed, it can goe no further, but to effect certain evils to afflict the relative, but to punish the cause, not formally to denominate the descendant or relative to be a Sinner</HI>; So he saith again, to which thus much is to be said; That what per∣haps may be congruously spoken betwixt one particular man and another, is very inconsutile to be said betwixt <HI>Adam</HI> and all Mankind. Betwixt Man and Man, we know the Descendants of Traitors and Vassals, in relation to their proge∣nitors
<PB N="43" REF="27"/>
offences, are punish'd, though they were not formally the Offenders: And therefore such words may say some∣thing, in respect of proximate Parents, and of relatives yet living, upon whom their condition may reflect, and to whom their example may be usefull; but in relation betwixt the prime Parent and us his descendants, they say nothing at all; For he was not punished for our Sins, but we for his; neither was he pu∣nished in our punishment, but we in his; neither was his simply another mans sin, but ours also; neither was it imputed only, but inherent also; nei∣ther were we <HI>Relatives</HI> only, but <HI>acces∣sories</HI> only; neither were we <HI>Descen∣dants</HI> only, but participants (all this is to be understood of the Common na∣ture, union, and <HI>representation</HI>) and therefore here was enough to denomi∣nate us formally to be Sinners. But I cannot but wonder at such a restrictive largness in the saying, <HI>Another mans sin imputed, therefore because it is ano∣thers and imputed.</HI> For the Sin or the crime to be imputed, therefore because it is imputed, and for the evil or punish∣ment to be inflicted for another mans
<PB N="44" REF="28"/>
sin therefore, because it is anothers; this is horrid to think of even in Men, what is it then to urge in such a case as this, where it cannot but reflect even upon God himself? But (about this im∣putation) he yet urges, <HI>Nor Reason, nor Sciptures, nor Religion does enforce, and no Divine attribute does permit that we should say that God did so impute</HI> Adams <HI>sin to his posterity, that he did really e∣steem them to be guilty of</HI> Adams <HI>sin, e∣qually culpable, equally hatefull:</HI> though this latter part be said but by few; yet this Scripture in hand inforces us to say, That God did really esteem them to be guilty of <HI>Adams</HI> Sin [<HI>in whom all have sinned</HI>] that is, really sinned, and by whose disobedience <HI>they were made Sin∣ners, sc.</HI> really so made; if he did so only impute, as not really and verily e∣steem guilty; what kind of imputation (I pray) was that? <HI>imaginative, opini∣onative, suspitious, pretensive, presump∣tive conjectural, phantastical, equivocal, abusive,</HI> or, (as are his own words) <HI>fi∣gurative, Metonymical, collateral, indi∣rect?</HI> this we are sure no <HI>Reason,</HI> no <HI>Scripture,</HI> no Religion, no Divine At∣tribute will permit to say so; But be∣cause
<PB N="45" REF="28"/>
he wil have us say <HI>equally culpable, equally hatefull,</HI> &amp;c. we will say it in the most convenient sense, we may be equal∣ly culpable in our common nature, e∣qually hatefull in our Natural Sin, the <HI>same Malice</HI> of our Nature, the same <HI>action</HI> of our Nature, <HI>as much guilty as he,</HI> according to that universal nature wherein he comprised and represented us all; and so much, he is not unknow∣ing all Religions (primitive and latter, Protestant and Papists) have said, not without reason and Scripture, nor is a∣ny Attribute of God to be objected there against. But to suppose <HI>that we have sinned</HI> (take us truly as in our Na∣ture, union, mass, root, stock, &amp;c.) <HI>less than he,</HI> or <HI>That God imputed this Sin lesse to us than to him</HI>; this (say we) is but supposition, and that is far from probation; and therefore we would fain learn that <HI>Analogie of Faith,</HI> those <HI>Words of Scripture,</HI> that <HI>proportion,</HI> and <HI>Notice</HI> of the Divine <HI>Attributes,</HI> that would inforce us to suppose so much. But I return to the <HI>Apostles supposition,</HI> who here supposes that there was no time of the world since the <HI>First mans fall,</HI> wherein there was not a Law, and
<PB N="46" REF="29"/>
sin and the imputation: How is it then that he says of Mankind? <HI>They did do actions unnatural and vile enough, but yet these sins were not yet so imputed</HI> — were they indeed unnatural and vile, and yet not so imputed? upon what ground then does he censure them for such? that cannot be but a calumnious aspersion, that prae-occupates the Law, and precedes the Divine <HI>Imputation</HI>; let him say how were they unnatural? but because done against the Law of Nature; and why vile enough? but because that pure and perfect law was sufficient so to convince them: Origi∣nal Sin could never have been called so, but that there was a Law of Original righteousness, that went before it; how then can actual sins be said to foregoe a Law? <HI>For they did do actions,</HI> personal, actual Sins, even these done, and <HI>yet not imputed</HI>? Oh, what an imputation were this to the eternal Law, the Law of Na∣ture, of right reason, and true Consci∣ence? But will this salve it to say, they were not <HI>yet so imputed</HI>? that will not do it; if he so means that nothing was impu∣ted from the first upon their Original account, to the eternal and internal; but
<PB N="47" REF="29"/>
afterwards, <HI>upon the external publica∣tion of the Law of Moses,</HI> these things were imputed to them upon their perso∣nal account; nor will that do it, if he pretends these things were not imputed <HI>even unto death:</HI> For it is out of questi∣on, that <HI>Moses</HI> Law (as to the morali∣ty of it) added no new vertue, goodness, truth, obligation, imputation or penalty, which was not in force before from the eternal and internal Law of God and Nature, of which <HI>Moses</HI> Law was no more but the <HI>External publication</HI>; but to speak of actual Sins being in Men, and yet not imputed by God, and of Origi∣ginal Sin deputed to deadly punishment, and yet not imputed by a Law, I say, to speak to such purposes, is such an im∣putation to the Divine Attributes, as I need not now to say.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="48" REF="30"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 14.</BIBL>
<Q>Nevertheless death reigned from Adam to Moses even over them that had not sinned after the simili∣tude of Adams transgression, who is the figure of him that is to come.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>NEvertheless Death reigned from</HI> A∣dam <HI>to</HI> Moses] But for all that the Law of <HI>Moses</HI> was not yet given or pro∣mulgated to a peculiar people; Death notwithstanding reigned throughout the whole world: For all that time (com∣prehensively and inclusively) from <HI>A∣dam</HI> his <HI>Fall,</HI> his deprivation of the I∣mage, and depravation of Nature; Till <HI>Moses</HI> his publication of the Law written in Tables of stone; and so du∣ring that whole <HI>Oeconomie</HI> or dispensati∣on, even until <HI>Christ</HI> and the <HI>Gospel</HI> of his Grace; by whom alone all that be∣leeve are justified from all things (both Sin and Death) from which they could not be justified by the Law of <HI>Moses.</HI> And therefore till then (terminally and exclusively) Death reigned, and Sin likewise; because the dominion and ty∣ranny of these two always goe together;
<PB N="49" REF="30"/>
Now after the duration, the main thing remarkable is the domination or <HI>Deaths reigning,</HI> which cannot exactly be, but as she is understood in her whole law and power, and in their full latitude or extent; <HI>sc.</HI> in the forcible denunciation, and infliction of Death <HI>temporal, spiritu∣al,</HI> and <HI>eternael</HI>; For where she is so restrained as to goe no farther than the corporal only, so far is she then from any thing like to reigning, that she is now, as it were, swallowed up in Vi∣ctory; but take her in her utmost Ty∣rany, and she reigned from <HI>Adam</HI> to <HI>Moses,</HI> that is, for Original, as well as for actual sin: for consider her subjects, and her power and authority was,</P>
<P><HI>Even over them that had not sinned af∣ter the similitude of</HI> Adams <HI>transgression,</HI> That is over Infants, whose reason and discretion, will, and affections, had not yet made them ripe enough for action and imitation; and therefore they had not sinned actually, or in their own persons, but Originally, or in their first Parents <HI>loyus. Adams similitude, likeness,</HI> or <HI>Image,</HI> in which he begat his Poste∣rity (<HI>Gen.</HI> 5. 3.) was that of Original sin, because it was contradistinct to that
<PB N="50" REF="31"/>
<HI>image, likeness,</HI> or <HI>similitude</HI> in which God had made him, (<HI>Gen.</HI> 1, 26, 27.) which was that of <HI>Original Righteousness.</HI> And to Sin after the similitude of <HI>Adams</HI> transgression, is, to imitate him, follow him, make him our example, and our selves altogether like him; and there∣fore not to have sinned after that simili∣tude, is, not to have done so. Now then to construe it (with this Author) <HI>of sin∣ning not so grievously,</HI> or <HI>of sinning lesse</HI> than he did, is to make it come little near to, nay, make it fall very much short of sinning after the similitude of his Transgression, or according to the proportion of his prevarication; To sin less, is, not to sin according to the aequal∣lity: But a man may sin less by much, and yet sin after the similitude neverthe∣less: He that ere this started this very notion (<HI>non peccaverunt ad illius simili∣tudinem; hoc est non tam capitaliter — non perinde graviter peccaverunt arque ille</HI>) applies it rather (as others besides him do) to the <HI>Gentiles</HI> than to the <HI>Patriarks,</HI> (and indeed in such a construction, the <HI>Gentiles</HI> should sin lesse than the <HI>Patri∣arks,</HI> as not having the Law, or the like means they had) But if the same Man
<PB N="51" REF="31"/>
had been taken up, or followed in his other suggestion (<HI>regnavit mors in simi∣tudine</HI>) the reigning of Death had so been made as vain a semblance, and as light a shadow, as some would make that of Original Sin. But they who suggest that this sinning after the simili∣tude, is neither to be understood of sin∣ning after an internal principle; nor yet after an external example; but only up∣on and after the direct expression, and express direction of a precept; These (ere they are a ware) do take from the Actual and add to the Original; while they thus exempt all before the written law, as likewise all <HI>Heathens,</HI> to this day, from sinning after <HI>Adams</HI> similitude, or rather doe thus deny to most men Sin both Original and Actual; but though we may make <HI>Adam</HI> a Sin similitude to our selves in matters past; yet it hath pleased God to propose him, as a com∣fortable <HI>type</HI> for the future.</P>
<P><HI>Who is the figure of him that was to come</HI>] Behold! here's a typical promise, sufficient to satisfie all querulous com∣plaining, and to prevent all quarrellous charging <HI>God</HI> foolishly, in calling any of his Articles to question in the case,
<PB N="52" REF="32"/>
Since <HI>Adam,</HI> who received Gods simili∣tude, not for himself alone, but for all his posterity after him, had now forfei∣ted the same both for himself and them all, and had now begotten them in his own similitude of prevarication and de∣fection; and in that very similitude they were now found, and so lest; left (and that justly) to the Tyranny of Sin and Death, yea even those, who had not as yet (according to all actual circumstan∣ces) sinned after the similitude of <HI>A∣dams</HI> transgression; Neverthelesse they were yet in the estate of Natural corrup∣tion, and by that Nature, worthily born Children of wrath; but what if they had already sinned after that simi∣litude, and had now made him their Example to sin, and to die by? yet hath God (of his good pleasure) made him the Type or figure of Christ, intimating that they who are elected by him, and beleeve in him, shall not die by the <HI>one,</HI> in whom they sinned; but shall live by the <HI>other,</HI> in whom they beleeved; For as the First man <HI>Adam,</HI> was the head and principle of Nature to us, and after that of Sin, so is this second <HI>Man Adam</HI> (<HI>Christ the Lord</HI>) the principle and
<PB N="53" REF="32"/>
head of Grace to us; and after that of Glory. Behold then (each one) the goodness and severity of God; On them which fell <HI>severity</HI>; But towards thee goodness if thou continue in his good∣ness: And thus indeed are the Divine Attributes to be magnified by us on either part.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="54" REF="33"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 15.</BIBL>
<Q>But not as the offence so al∣so is the free gift: for if through the offence of one many be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one Man Ie∣sus Christ, hath abounded unto many.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>BUt not as the offence so also is the free gift</HI>] The Comparison is now not interrupted, but pursued with a corre∣ction; For he confesses that in the Ana∣logy there lies a great deal of disparity. There may be a <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or some re∣semblance between the persons; as each of them being the First, the Author, the Head, the Root, the Foundation, the Representative of his kind but there is a <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, an utter difference of the things; as betwixt Sin and Grace, Death and Life: And therefore though there may be comparing of the persons, with an infinite preferring on the one part; yet there can be no conferring of the things, but with an utter differing, both for ac∣count, and effect; because there may be some Typical proportion betwixt <HI>A∣dam</HI>
<PB N="55" REF="33"/>
and <HI>Christ,</HI> with the due honour re∣served to the <HI>Great Reconciler</HI>; but be∣twixt the <HI>offence</HI> of one, and the <HI>Free gift</HI> of the other, remains an utter dis∣proportion, never to be reconciled: For the one both is from, and is the I∣mage of the <HI>Earthly,</HI> the other is from, and is the Image of the <HI>Heavenly</HI>; the one is naturally transmitted, the other supernaturally conferred; the one from Free-will, the other from Free grace; the one tending to Death, but the other to everlasting life.</P>
<P><HI>For if through the offence of one many be dead, &amp;c.</HI>] In this part of the colla∣tion, this is one main instance of prela∣tion from the disparity of power and ef∣fect, as if he had thus said, suppose the worst that followed Original Sin, that innace offence; yet forasmuch as the re∣medy propounded so far exceeded the propagated malady, what cause is here to complain or challenge any of the <HI>Di∣vine Attributes</HI>? since wisdom herein manifests and magnifies her self so excel∣lently, so exceedingly, (both for sub∣stance and measure) why should not her children herein seek to justifie her herein above all? what if it was through the
<PB N="56" REF="34"/>
<HI>offence of one,</HI> ought that to offend? were we not one Nature, one <HI>Species</HI> of Men, both he and we? In the participa∣tion of that <HI>Species,</HI> all men were to be reckoned as one Man, the sundry per∣sons of men being to that one Man, but as the several Members are to the same body: Moreover this may be enough to satisfie all minds, and stop all mouths; <HI>The Grace of God, and the gift of Grace,</HI> (both his liberal favour, and our com∣petent measure) <HI>is also by one Man Ie∣sus Christ</HI>: And why then should we set our selves to wrangle so, with God, with our selves, and one another, be∣cause of the Justice and Severity which descends to us but duly from <HI>the one</HI> in one way; and not rather rest our selves contented, and greatly rejoyce, for the <HI>Grace</HI> and <HI>Mercy</HI> that most freely and superabundantly proceeds towards <HI>us</HI> from <HI>that one man Iesus Christ</HI> another way? Oh! what peevish things we are! to vex our selves in thinking, how we were made subject to the punishment on the one hand; when we might sweetly satisfie our selves, in beleeving how we are made capable of the exceeding re∣compence of reward on the other. And
<PB N="57" REF="34"/>
grant again by the <HI>first one,</HI> and through his one way <HI>many be dead,</HI> understand it withall emphatically spoken <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; <HI>the many,</HI> that is <HI>All</HI>; for it is not <HI>ma∣ny</HI> comparatively, but absolutely; not so spoken as to except some, but to intimate <HI>All</HI>; <HI>All</HI> (I say) collectively, and inclusively, and not so sparingly or seemingly (as he speaks) <HI>even as it were all, Enoch also</HI> (contrary to his mind) <HI>not excepted</HI>: how much less <HI>those few more, of whom peradventure mention is not made</HI>? The first is a fond conceit, but the next a vainer crotchet: For take <HI>Many</HI> (as he would) in the restrained way, and <HI>Dead,</HI> but for corporally so; yet even <HI>Enoch</HI> was among that <HI>many,</HI> &amp; so is dead; For it is not his peculiar and abstruse way of dying that can hinder to say truly <HI>he is dead</HI>; For <HI>Heb.</HI> 11. 7. though he was translated by an extraor∣dinary power, <HI>that he should not see Death,</HI> after the common way; yet for the verity and reality of Death, it was said of him together with the rest; <HI>These all died,</HI> vers. 13. But taking it (according to the <HI>Apostle</HI>) in the largest sense. I must say more, <HI>All</HI> are dead, namely, though not effectually, yet virtually;
<PB N="58" REF="35"/>
though not naturally, yet deservedly; according to a just sentence, though not according to the fearfull Execution; But notwithstanding all this, and all that can be said of the offences worst, and Death's utmost; how would it ap∣pease our consciences, and comfort our spirits (even in all wherein the Divine Majesty has been pleased to reveal, ei∣ther himself, or our selves to us) to conceive rightly, and heartily consider <HI>the grace of God,</HI> which is to be under∣stood his good will and pleasure, free goodnesse, everlasting love, exceeding favour, with all his <HI>beloved Sons</HI> merits, and <HI>Holy Spirits</HI> efficacies, and <HI>the gift</HI> by <HI>Grace,</HI> sc. our measures of Sanctifi∣cation, with the duties required, the comforts promised, and the benefits re∣ceived? And all this by <HI>One man Iesus Christ,</HI> sc. by his life and actions; by his death and passion; by his merits and mediation alone. To whom we had no natural, or necessary relation (as we had unto the other) but as he was made Man, and so freely and gratiously gave himself to us, and for us. And thus the grace of God hath much more abound∣ed in pardoning all kinds and measures
<PB N="59" REF="35"/>
of sin, and in preventing the same, as concerning punishment: But the <HI>Free gift hath abounded also,</HI> we being made both more holy and more hap∣py in <HI>Christ</HI> than in <HI>Adam,</HI> we were made corrupt, and miserable, yea and this abounded unto <HI>Many,</HI> that is <HI>All</HI> again, and that in sufficiency, though not in effect, else the excess here spoken of should fall short; inasmuch as Sin and Death passed upon <HI>All.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="60" REF="36"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 16.</BIBL>
<Q>And not as it was by one that sinned, so is the gift; for the judgement was by one to condemna∣tion, but the Free gift is of many of∣fences unto justification.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>ANd not as it was by one that sinned, so is the gift</HI>] It is partly a repeti∣tion of the first words in the former verse; only there was the Disparity and excess betwixt the Sin and the Grace; here betwixt the Gift, and the person sinning: There it was said to be more plentifully abounding, here more pow∣erfully effecting; There by what Au∣thors, here to what Ends; There the Free gift was opposed to the Sin, but here to the Judgement.</P>
<P><HI>For the Iudgement was by one to con∣demnation</HI>] By the Judgement we un∣derstand not only the Decree on God's part, but also the desert on our own; In as much as the word in Scripture notes both the Act and the power of Judgement, as likewise the cause and thing judged: And if we did but truly consider this, then durst we not be so
<PB N="61" REF="36"/>
bold in questioning the Divine Attri∣butes, in regard we are taught to appre∣hend it as a thing not only of his <HI>severi∣ty,</HI> but of our own impiety also: So by <HI>Condemnation</HI> we understand both the <HI>Sentence</HI> and <HI>Execution</HI>; the <HI>threatning</HI> against, as well as the <HI>inflicting</HI> on; likewise we take the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) in the Neuter; as wee doe the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) in the Masculine; yea and from the di∣verse preposition, we note some distin∣ction, namely of the matter and subject, as well as of the cause and instrument: and thereupon we doe not confound them (as he doth) by <HI>One Man sinning one sin</HI>; but somewhat more distinctly, by <HI>one sinning,</HI> or <HI>that sinned,</HI> we un∣derstand the Act with relation to <HI>A∣dams</HI> person; but by the <HI>one sin</HI> we un∣derstand the thing it self with relation to our whole Nature, even Original sin it self, to note that <HI>one sin</HI> (original sin) in us, is under the same judgement unto condemnation, as was that <HI>one sinning</HI> in <HI>Adam</HI>; and that in the very Act of his sinning, <HI>we sinned</HI> (as he seems to grant) <HI>ve<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y much</HI>: And moreover to that, sinned (which he grants not) as bad as he &amp; that not only <HI>because of the
<PB N="92" REF="37"/>
likeness of Nature, and of sin</HI> (as he says) but because of the very identity and sameness thereof, in the main substance, though not according to every circum∣stance; For we <HI>Descendents from A∣dam, were perfectly like him in nature, his own real, natural production, and so we sinned,</HI> as himself says well; and now if he himself thinks there is <HI>so great a pa∣rity of reason that the evil</HI> (he means this judgement unto condemnation) <HI>should descend upon us</HI>; then in all reason he ought to yeeld not only a likeness, but also a parity of Sin. Yet whereas he says, <HI>the evil was threatned to Adam, and not to his Children</HI>: Then was it not judgement <HI>unto condemnation,</HI> for judgement implies the <HI>Sentence</HI> and Commination, as Condemnation does the <HI>Execution,</HI> or effect. But what? not <HI>threatned,</HI> and yet <HI>descending</HI>? will <HI>the Lord</HI> strike before he warns? I say no more, but (for Gods sake) what kind of Vindication call you that? to urge the evil or punishment so oft, and ad∣mit so little of the fault or sin, is (I think verily) the wrong way to a Vin∣dication of the <HI>Divine Attributes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But the Free gift is, of many offences
<PB N="63" REF="37"/>
unto justification</HI>] To prevent all our murmuring and censuring, that judge∣ment should be to condemnation by one man or person, the Apostle bids us con∣strue him rightly, and says he means it by one <HI>Sin</HI> or <HI>offence</HI>; for we shall ne∣ver think Gods ways equal in this case, till we can look upon it with a right Eye, not only as the Sin of one man, and so the Sin of another; But as one sin of all men, and so our own: But the Sin of one, and one Sin, if this satisfie not; yet this makes amends for all abundantly; that the <HI>Free gift is of many offeuces unto justification.</HI> For mark how it answers to every opposite, the <HI>Free gift</HI> to the <HI>offence, many</HI> to <HI>one,</HI> and <HI>justification</HI> to <HI>condemnation.</HI> The first shews how benignly, the next, how bountifully, the last how beneficially the recompense is vouchsafed; as it is the Free gift to the offence; so it signs Grace in us not to be natural, as the sin is. As it is <HI>many</HI> to <HI>one</HI>; so it betokens a liberal condo∣nation of many actuals, as well as that one Original. As it is <HI>Iustification</HI> a∣gainst <HI>condemnation</HI>; so it signifies a making holy as well as happy, against both the sin and the punishment. Since
<PB N="64" REF="38"/>
then what <HI>God</HI> in <HI>Christ</HI> hath here done, is to justifie; let God in Christ be justi∣fied by all, and in all.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 14.</BIBL>
<Q>For if by one mans offence Death reigned by one, much more they who receive abundance of grace, and of the gift of Righteousness, shall reign in life by one Iesus Christ.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>FOr if by one Man's offence Death reigned by one</HI>] It is of no small note, that a mutual construction is here to be made of <HI>one Mans offence,</HI> and <HI>one offence</HI>: The diverse reading shews a co∣incidence; and however the repetition seems as the note upon their narrow conjunction; nothing has done more prejudice to the truth of this point, and to the Divine Attributes, as they are therein concerned, than a dividing, se∣parating, or over-severe and too nice distinguishing between the <HI>one man,</HI> and the <HI>one offence</HI>; For though the natural corruption may be distinguishd from the personal Act; according to some circum∣stances,
<PB N="65" REF="38"/>
yet in substance they are to be considered as one, and the same, be∣cause it was (for the main substance) the same sin that <HI>Adam</HI> committed, that entred into the world by him; and well might the same sin passe from the whole, or head, into all the parts, &amp; members; though not in the particular Act, yet in the universal guilt; so that in his very sin we might (not amiss) be said to sin originally, although not actually. The <HI>Apostle</HI> more than once expresly inti∣mates it to be translated indifferently, ei∣ther the Sin <HI>and offence of one man,</HI> or <HI>one sin</HI> and <HI>offence.</HI> We should do well therefore to accept it so equally, as he hath been pleased to expresse it: But we look askew upon it, in the personal Act only; as that <HI>one mans</HI> sin, and no more; and so we ascribe and impute all to him most presumptuously; and seek in like manner to shake it off from our selves. Strange it is! we dare not deny that God imputes it to us; and yet we dare be bold to impute it solely to him. For so the <HI>Paraphrast</HI> seems to do: <HI>The Sin of Adam alone,</HI> whereas (in truth) we ought humbly to conceive, and consider it as <HI>one Sin,</HI> both in him, and us; <HI>one
<PB N="66" REF="39"/>
Sin</HI> in our Nature, <HI>one Sin</HI> in our kind: and so coming to be but one Sin even in the persons of us all. They that goe the first way, are quite out of the way to vindicate the Divine Attributes; For how is it possible to make it anothers sin alone, and not our own in any proper respect, and yet not give occasion to murmurers and repiners at the imputati∣on, to any purpose whatsoever. Where∣as if instead of imposing it altogether upon another, we would be convinc'd and content to take what is our own, un∣to our selves, That heavy yoak which is upon the Sons of <HI>Adam,</HI> from the day that they goe out of their Mothers womb, till the day that they return to the Mother of all things, would not be so grievous, or so unequal to their ap∣prehensions; But they would soon be convinc'd to lay their hands upon their mouths; yea would be content to say every man for himself, This is my Yoak (the image of the earthy) and I will bear it; I will bear the indignation of the Lord, <HI>because I have sinned against him</HI>; which is never to be brought to passe if we once go about to unyoak our selves of the Sin: But whether we will
<PB N="67" REF="39"/>
do so or no, God will be true when all men are found Lyers; his ways will be proved equal, when our ways are repro∣ved for unequal; and wisdom will be justified and cleared, when she is judged, though no flesh living can be justified in her sight. The very punishment and infliction from God, is sufficient to ar∣gue the sin and guilt in us: <HI>For Death reigned by one,</HI> not only <HI>by one man,</HI> in the Masculine (as he spake immediately before) but <HI>by one in the Neuter,</HI> one Sin; for death could never so have reigned by the one <HI>Man,</HI> had it not been by the one sin: Yet see how he would labour to bring the Original punishment on our heads, that will not admit us to bring the Original Sin so much as upon our <HI>Shoulders</HI>: For so he supposes it: <HI>If the sin of Adam alone could bring death upon the world, who by imitation of his transgression, on the stock of their own natural choice did sin, against God, though not after the similitude of A∣dams transgression.</HI> How says he? no Sin but in imitation? no punishment but for imitation? he knows full well whose exploded heresie that was, and there∣fore shall do very well to renounce both
<PB N="70" REF="40"/>
name and thing at once. But how a∣gree his own words to themselves? <HI>sin∣ning by imitation, and yet not after the si∣militude of Adams transgression?</HI> (which cannot genuinely, no nor conveniently be interpreted but of sinning actually, and by imitation; yea let it be under∣stood of sinning less than he did, yet so it is by imitation.) Again, <HI>Sinning on the stock of their own natural choice,</HI> and yet, <HI>not sinning after the similitude of A∣dams transgression</HI>? Why how sinned <HI>Adam</HI> but out of the stock of his own na∣tural choice? And how sinned we in <HI>him,</HI> but out of the stock of his natural choice? for indeed he was our natural stock, and we were the branches there∣of: And it was he that received the whole stock of Natures choice, liberty, Free will, and consent for himself, and likewise for us all; and out of this stock of natural choice and liberty it was, that we sinned not only by him, but in him, and with him; wherefore I heartily wish him to be wary how he exempts <HI>sinning after the similitude of Adams transgressi∣on,</HI> and sinning on the stock of our own natural choice, each from other, lest he imp<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir that stock, and overthrow that
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
Rock of liberty, and Free will, which (against both <HI>Supralapsarians,</HI> and <HI>Sub∣lapsarians</HI>) he laboured ere while so ear∣nestly to establish, and so prove to strike upon them, and himself, and the <HI>Divine Attributes,</HI> all at once. But (to remedy all this) here it is not only by <HI>one Man,</HI> who had his personal choice, but by <HI>one sin,</HI> wherein was our natural choice; and therefore let us go on to see what the <HI>Apostle</HI> inferrs, and preferrs in such a case.</P>
<P>— <HI>How much more they which receive abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteousnesse shall reign in life by one Io∣sus Christ</HI>] sc. Though Death reigned much both by one man, and by one sin; yet by one Christ they shall reign much more. But then they must be due∣ly qualified, for it is <HI>They which re∣ceive,</HI> and that argues no capacity, no ability in them, notwithstanding the blemish of Orginal sin, for thereby they were under Death's reign, which was spiritual and not corporal only; and held under the power, and utter slavery of Sin as well as Death; rather it con∣vinces them of their privation and im∣potence, as not having but as they re∣ceive;
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="70" REF="41"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="71" REF="41"/>
<PB N="72" REF="42"/>
yet notwithstanding such empti∣ness and unaptness, being prepared and embled by <HI>Christs abundance,</HI> they must <HI>receive</HI> (that is rightly apply) <HI>Grace,</HI> sc. the grace of justification by Faith, and likewise the <HI>Gift of Righte∣ousness,</HI> sc. the sanctification of the Spi∣rit to holy walking: And both these they shall have, both in their kinds and measures, <HI>sc. abundance,</HI> namely, for sufficiency, but not to <HI>supererogation</HI>: And <HI>so they shall reign in life</HI>; sc. from Vassals under Sin and Death, become Free-men, nay Kings in life, both of Grace and Glory. And all this not of themselves, nor for any worthiness of their own, but by the sole merits and mediation of <HI>one Iesus Christ,</HI> who is <HI>God</HI> all-sufficient, and besides whom there is no <HI>Saviour.</HI> All these Excel∣lencies of Remedy put together, serve but to set forth the destituteness and de∣sperateness of the <HI>Disease.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="73" REF="42"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 18.</BIBL>
<Q>Therefore, as by the of∣fence of one Iudgement came upon all men, to condemnation; even so by the righteousness, of one, the Free gift came upon all men unto justification of life.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>THerefore as by the offence of one man judgement came upon all men,</HI> &amp;c.] This 18 verse, by the illative, seems (to me) rather to refer to the 16 verse than to any of the rest, and may thence more expresly and peculiarly be supplyed. Howbeit the Comparison was there with more precise respect to the Things; hu<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> here to the persons. <HI>Therefore then</HI> (the illative is a reduplicate, and con∣cludes so much the stronger) <HI>as by the of∣fence of one man,</HI> or <HI>by one offence</HI> (whether the primordial Act of his person, or the original stain of our Nature) <HI>judgement</HI> (of the Divine Decree, so wise, so just) <HI>came upon all men</HI> (all common men, and born after the ordinary way of Na∣ture, not the <HI>blessed Virgin,</HI> none but Christ himself excepted) <HI>unto condemna∣tion</HI> (at least from his sentence, and ac∣cording
<PB N="74" REF="43"/>
to our desert) <HI>even so by the righteousnesse</HI> (of his person, natures, offices) <HI>the Free gift</HI> (of grace and sal∣vation; <HI>came upon all men</HI> (sufficiently, yea, and effectually too upon all the faithfull, For he is the <HI>Saviour</HI> of all men, especially of those that beleeve) <HI>unto justification of life,</HI> sc. that life which only the justified, or which by justifi∣cation only, all men attain unto. And here I have only those words of his to except against: <HI>The proportion and com∣parison lies in the mayn emanation of death, from one, and life from the other.</HI> That certainly it does not, if we look at the Comparison no further than as it lies in the present verse; for here the main proportion and comparison is be∣twixt <HI>the offence of one</HI> and <HI>the righ∣teousness of one,</HI> both here and through∣out the whole Comparison <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Grace,</HI> the <HI>offence</HI> and the <HI>free-gift,</HI> these are the main opposites; as being the principal causes: The other two <HI>Death</HI> and <HI>Life</HI> are but secondarily set oppo∣site, as being but the consequents or ef∣fects: And this I note that <HI>Christs</HI> excel∣lency might appear much more in reme∣dying the cause, than in removing the effect only.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="73" REF="43"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Verse 19.</BIBL>
<Q>For as by one Mans diso∣bedience many were made Sinners: so by the obedience of one, shall many be made righteous.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><HI>FOr as by one man's disobedience many were made Sinners</HI>] here concludes the comparison betwixt <HI>Adam</HI> and <HI>Christ</HI>; and he says well, <HI>this is the sum of all</HI>; for 'tis the principal scope of the <HI>Holy Ghost,</HI> to prefer <HI>Christ</HI> making righteous, to <HI>Adam</HI> making sinners. And therefore he saith yet better, <HI>we are made much more righteous by Christ, than we were sinners by Adam</HI>; and yet best of all, <HI>the graces we derive from Christ shall be more and mightier than the cor∣ruption and declination by Adom</HI>; be∣cause the excess and excellency of <HI>Christ</HI> appeareth much more in taking away the Sin and corruption, than in a deli∣vering from the misery and mortality of Original Sin; And therefore the <HI>Apo∣stle</HI> (in this case and comparison) con∣cludes it for his greatest glory in making Sinners righteous; above that of ma∣king the miserable happy, or bringing
<PB N="74" REF="44"/>
those that were subject to Death, to reign in life, saying thus, as the sum of all, <HI>as by one mans disobedience</HI> (<HI>Adams</HI> prime and personal Act, with all the af∣fections and circumstances) <HI>Many, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> the many</HI> (that is <HI>all</HI>; for none that ordinarily proceeded out of his loyns are to be excepted) <HI>were made Sinners</HI> (from and in that very Act, not only imputed and accounted, but con∣stituted, and really so effected) And so the very word is used both by St. <HI>Paul</HI> in this place, and by St. <HI>Peter,</HI> 2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 1. 8. and by St. <HI>Iames, Iam.</HI> 4. 4. to signi∣fie the very being of the thing, and not the bare reckoning only: And we may take his own construction of the word, <HI>put into the order of sinners</HI>; but then we understand it of the humane and natural order, as by generation and propagati∣on, and the like, but not of the divine and eternal order, <HI>as made such by Gods appointment.</HI> It stranges me still, that he who even now was so vehemently in∣vective against both <HI>Supralapsarians,</HI> and <HI>Sublapsarians,</HI> upon the account of the horrible and necessitating Decree, in this case of Original Sin, as reproving their supposition, <HI>if it be by the Decree
<PB N="75" REF="44"/>
of God by his choice and constitution, that it should be so, &amp;c.— and again, —if God may ordain men to Hell for Adams Sin, which is derived to them by Gods only con∣stitution, &amp;c.</HI>— And now for all that that himself is here, saying, <HI>many were constituted or put into the order of sinners; they were made such by Gods appointment</HI>; to speak altogether so like them: Is this the way (I pray you) to vindicate the Divine Attributes against them? nor will such an exception salve it at all, to say, <HI>not that God could be the Author of a Sin to any; but that he appointed the evil, which is the consequent of Sin to be upon their heads who descended from the Sin∣ner</HI>: For though Sin and the Sinner may be put for the punishment and the punished in some other places of Scrip∣ture, yet can neither be so understood or accepted in this to the <HI>Romans</HI>; be∣cause the Sin and the punishment both are here noted again and again in their proper, plain, and distinct expressions and comparisons. Neither is there truth (much lesse safety to the Divine Attri∣butes) to speak in such a sense, as, <HI>that God appointed</HI> (by his Decree) <HI>the evil</HI> (of punishment and misery) <HI>which is the
<PB N="76" REF="45"/>
consequent of Sin,</HI> (anothers, and not their own) <HI>to be upon their heads</HI> (out∣wardly and temporally, though the pravity was never in their hearts) <HI>who descended from the Sinner</HI> (and yet de∣scended not Sinners themselves) For thus (though he labours not to speak out) a man of any strict observation, or narrow search, must needs accept him, and the rather, because of former pas∣sages to this purpose not a few; besides what necessity is there to wrap in here the divine constituting (either for sin or suffering) where the humane constitu∣ting is so evident, so sufficient? It is but asking by whom or by what were many made sinners? and the answer is here al∣ready made to our hands, <HI>by one Mans disobedience,</HI> to bid us satisfie all our cu∣riosity in that; and to seek no further for a constituting cause; nor indeed will the whole Analogie endure it; For the total comparison is not betwixt <HI>God</HI> and <HI>Christ,</HI> but betwixt <HI>Christ</HI> and <HI>Adam</HI>; neither is all this excesse, or excellence of State (wherein Christ constituted us, above that wherein <HI>Adam</HI> destituted us) spoken with any respect to God; but in a direct and compleat respect to <HI>Adam</HI> only.</P>
<P><PB N="77" REF="45"/><HI>So by the obedience of one shall many be made righteous</HI>] <HI>By the obedience</HI> (both active and passive) <HI>of one</HI> (Lord Jesus Christ, who alone is sufficient to satis∣fie for all sins original and actual) <HI>shall many,</HI> even all the Elect, all that be∣leeve) <HI>be made righteous,</HI> made (as himself says well) <HI>and constituted righte∣ous</HI>: And we hope he means really righ∣teous (by the <HI>Spirits</HI> imparting as well as <HI>Christs</HI> imputing) else where were all this contrariety of the Comparison? For what excesse or excellency were it, to make a thing really righteous, if it was not really sinfull and corrupt before? and <HI>righteous,</HI> that is, not only happy, but holy withall; And therefore the Sinners must needs be understood, not only as miserable and afflicted, but as <HI>declined</HI> and <HI>corrupted</HI>; and so signify∣ing, we joyn with him (as we have al∣ready approved him) in what he says to the end of the <HI>Paraphrase</HI>; Neverthe∣less we may not doe so as touching the <HI>Consequents</HI> or <HI>Antecedents</HI> thereof; <HI>Therefore.</HI></P>
<DIV3 TYPE="item">
<PB N="78" REF="46"/>
<HEAD>1. As to the Antecedents.</HEAD>
<P>HIs Position which he intimates in opposition to the Objection is, <HI>That to deny original sin to be a sin proper∣ly, and inherently, is not expresly against the words of St.</HI> Paul <HI>in the</HI> 5 <HI>chapter to the Romans.</HI> And for this he hath these sayings; (For as for reasons, he hath more reason than to call them so) 1. He supposes, <HI>the words are capable of interpretation, otherwise than is vul∣garly pretended.</HI> Now I suppose that the interpretation of the Primitive Churches, Councils, Fathers, Papists, Protestants, Lutherans, Calvinists, (and the most learned and moderate of them) is of other account with him, than ei∣ther as vulgar, or as pretended. Yea a reason (or the Maior of it) is propound∣ed by him. <HI>For any interpretation that does violence to right reason, to Religion, to holinesse of life, and the divine Attri∣butes of God, is therefore to be rejected, and another chosen.</HI> True! but then it re∣mains on his part to be proved, That such an Interpretation (as is contrary to his understandiug) does so in all, or in
<PB N="79" REF="46"/>
some one of them at least: And withall, that an Interpretation of his own under∣standing be not such in all or any one of them. 2. <HI>Sin in the Scripture is taken for the punishment</HI>; what then? it is not so here, nor in more than hundreds of pla∣ces besides. For as <HI>life</HI> and <HI>death</HI> go all along the <HI>Antithesis</HI> throughout for the express <HI>reward</HI> and <HI>punishment,</HI> so doe <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Righteousnesse,</HI> the <HI>offence</HI> and the <HI>Free gift</HI> distinctly, as the vile ano∣mie or obliquity; or as the holy vertue or efficacy. 3. The word <HI>Condemnation</HI> is <HI>by the Apnstle himself limited to signifie Temporal death</HI>; no such matter by his favour, for most certain it is <HI>condemna∣tion</HI> is here opposed by him, to the <HI>Iu∣stification of life</HI>; and that signifies life, both spiritual and eternal; and to take away the extent on either part, is rather to make the <HI>Apostle</HI> limit the excess on the best part. <HI>He must mean Temporal death, for eternal death did not passe upon all men.</HI> Yes, that it did even passe upon all men, from the just sentence; though (as he knows who said) it did not <HI>in∣vade</HI> all men, to an uttermost Execution. <HI>And if he means eternal death, he must not mean that it came from Adams sin,
<PB N="80" REF="47"/>
but in as much as all have sinned, &amp;c.</HI> well corrected of himself, but ill re∣strained by him. Yea, indeed but he must; and very well he may; not only, <HI>in as much as,</HI> but <HI>in whom</HI> all have sin∣ned: Even originally, in his loyns; al∣though not actually in themselves. If all have sinned in him, an eternal death is little enough: But if not, even a Tem∣poral death is too much. 4. <HI>The Apo∣stle here speaks of sin imputed, therefore not of sin inherent</HI>; why not one as well as the other? imputed and inherent, though they may be of some diverse con∣sideration, yet are they not of such con∣trariety, that they may consist toge∣ther, and that in every kind of sin. As actual sin is inherent, and yet neverthe∣less is imputed; so original sin may be imputed, and yet inherent nevertheless; will the imputation, which is in respect of a Law, take away the inhaesion of the fact or crime, which is with respect to the person? Neither doth the Apostle speak here directly of Sin <HI>imputed</HI> but of Sin <HI>not imputed.</HI> And he knows that hath been construed by many, for man's not so re∣puting it, (through want of knowledge, or conscience of a law) although it was
<PB N="81" REF="47"/>
never so much inherent. 5. <HI>The Apo∣stle says, by the disobedience of one man many were made Sinnere: so that it ap∣pears, that in this we have no sin of our own; neither is it at all our own formally &amp; inherently.</HI> Whatsoever the appearance may be to us; yet this is of no conse∣quence from the words: Because <HI>Adam</HI> is here often called <HI>one,</HI> and <HI>one man</HI>; not so much to distinguish, or to divide him from us; but to compare and parallel him with Christ: And though it be cal∣led <HI>one man's disobedience,</HI> in regard of the individual, and circumstantial Act; yet in regard of the specifical Act of the Common Nature, the common union, comprehension, representation, it was indeed all our act. <HI>For so all have sinned</HI> and <HI>are made Sinners,</HI> sc. inherently. The Formality of Sin (whether original or actual) is anomie and obliquity to the Law of God, and so it is imputed; but with all it is <HI>ataxie</HI> and deformity of our nature, and so it is inherent; Nei∣ther was <HI>Adams</HI> Sin efficiently his per∣sons only, but his natures also, and so it was ours. And for Original Sin <HI>A∣dam's</HI> person was but the <HI>External</HI> effici∣ent; but the <HI>internal</HI> efficient was that
<PB N="82" REF="48"/>
law of corrupted Nature, whereby a corrupt thing deserted, did beget a cor∣rupt thing like it self, so that, that which is born of flesh, is flesh: But for him to make it <HI>effectively ours as to some purpo∣ses of imputation.</HI> Alas! this is to bring God into the business; whose wisdom and justice (no doubt) was efficient to some sad effects of punishment; but then to say, <HI>That it could not be a Sin in us formally</HI>: and notwithstanding the Divine Justice both imputing and effe∣cting such fearfull purposes, as the dreadfull and direfull effects of <HI>Adam's</HI> and our <HI>Original Sin, oh, Divine At∣tributes</HI>! What's now become of your <HI>Vinditation?</HI> I have heard of deputation to punishment, but not of imputation without the crime or fault. And if it be so that <HI>the sin ran in no sence be properly ours</HI>; how stands this with the Divine Justice, that the punishment should be ours in any sense whatsoever? since e∣ven we our selves (such is our natural and humane Justice) kill or destroy not poysonous Serpents, noisom vermin, savage Beasts, ravenous Birds; or pesti∣lent weeds; but for some natural vitio∣sity, seminally, innately, hereditarily,
<PB N="83" REF="48"/>
intrinsecally, inherently, formally and properly in them. 6. To his sixth say∣ing I have spoken before particularly, and say now moreover in summe, That it is not our punishment that can re∣dound to <HI>Adam,</HI> but the guilt of his sin rather that redounds upon us. That in actual, external, and particular Sins, it may be just to afflict the relatives; not only to punish the cause, but (for ter∣rors sake) to prevent the example; but in this original, internal, natural, and universal Sin, it cannot be for terror or prevention to any; since all are guilty, all are punished: That in our relation to <HI>Adam,</HI> we are not only descendants from him in our persons, but partici∣pants with him in our Natures, and so may be formally denominated <HI>Sinners</HI> as well as he: And if there be no more con∣tradiction in it, than for every man to say thus, <HI>if I am formally by him a Sin∣ner, then I did really doe his action</HI>: that may be easily said, and not so easie to be contradicted. For what hinders but that a man may say, nay, that he ought to say; I did really doe his action, though not in the personal and external circum∣stance, yet in the natural and internal
<PB N="84" REF="49"/>
substance of doing, I did really doe his action in his loyns, and as a member of of the whole body of Nature; Now if the Member of a mans body may for∣mally be denominated sinfull from the sin of the whole man: why then may not every man be so denominated here, being an included Member of the whole body of Mankind? 7. He says, <HI>there is nothing in the design or purpose of the A∣postle, that can or ought to enforce any other thing,</HI> than what? <HI>than that we sinned lesse than</HI> Adam, <HI>and therefore sin∣ned not in him,</HI> and <HI>that God imputed this sin less to us, than to him.</HI> I confesse I can see no such purpose in the <HI>Apostle,</HI> and doubtlesse his design (throughout the whole contraposition) is not to lessen our sin to <HI>Adams</HI>; but to lessen both <HI>Adams</HI> sinne, and the sinne of <HI>us</HI> all, to <HI>Christs righteousnesse</HI>; yea and to lessen the Death which both he and we deser∣ved, to the <HI>life</HI> that <HI>Christ</HI> had merited for us; and so indeed, to heighten his Acts and Attributes in all. But thus he argues, <HI>If we have sinned less, then we did not sin in him.</HI> To which it may be thus answered, the hand sins less than the mind, did it not therefore sin in the
<PB N="85" REF="49"/>
body? but we see no reason why we should not still say; we sinned in him (naturally though not personally) <HI>and as much as he,</HI> neither do we look that our sin in him, should <HI>by him be lessened to us,</HI> but by <HI>Christ</HI> only, both to him, and to us all.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="item">
<HEAD>2. Now for the Consequents of this Paraphrase.</HEAD>
<P><HI>THe consequent of this discourse</HI> (he says) <HI>must needs be this at least.</HI> If it be consequent to his discourse so: but it stands us in hand to examine, whe∣ther it be consequent to the <HI>Apostles</HI> words: but since he will needs impose them on us as <HI>Consequences,</HI> he will not be angry if I take them up as <HI>Inconsequen∣ces:</HI> For whether so or so, I refer them, Sir, both to yours, and every able and indifferent mans judgement (Conseq.) <HI>That it is impossible that the greatest part of mankind, should be left in the eter∣ternal bonds of Hell by Adam.</HI> Incon∣sequ. nothing is impossible with God, nothing is impossible that is just∣ly
<PB N="86" REF="50"/>
done, and past; we say, not only the greatest part, but the whole race of mankind was so left; and yet all that aggravates it not to an impossibility. For why should it be thought an impos∣sibility, That all by <HI>Adam</HI> should be left in the etetnal bonds of Hell; since all in <HI>Adam</HI> had a possibility to be brought to the eternal Throne of <HI>Hea∣ven</HI>? (<HI>Conseq.</HI>) <HI>For then quite contrary to the discourse of the Apostle, there had been abundance of Sin, but a scarci∣ty of Grace; and the excesse had been on the part of</HI> Adam, <HI>not on the part of</HI> Christ. (Inconseq.) The abundance, or excess, which the <HI>Apostle</HI> here contends for, is not with respect to numbers or to multi∣tudes of persons, on either part, but in regard to Grace abounding Sin, and Life excelling Death, and <HI>Christs</HI> me∣rits infinitely exceeding both <HI>Adams</HI> and <HI>our own</HI> deserts. (Conseq.) <HI>So that the Presbyterian way is perfectly condemned by this discourse of the Apostle.</HI> (In∣conseq.) Though he tell them never so often, yet they will hardly beleeve him on his own word, till he can convince them from the <HI>Apostles</HI> words perfectly and indeed. (Conseq.) <HI>Nay, and yet
<PB N="87" REF="50"/>
more particularly convince them, when their way of understanding in this point, is singular from the Church of England, or other reformed Churches Suffrage; the other m<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re gentle way, which affirms that we were sentenc'd in Adam to eternal death, though the Execution is taken off by Christ, is also no way countenanced by any thing in this Chapter</HI>; (Inconseq.) No? these words (<HI>death passed, death reigned, the judgement was to condem∣nation</HI>) these (I say) countenance and confirm the sentence. Again (<HI>the Free gift came to justification of life, they shall reign in life by one Iesus Christ</HI>) these countenance and confirm the taking off the Execution; were it not thus both for the sentence and for the Execution, where then were all those excesses on <HI>Christs</HI> part? what excesse were it to make those righteous, that were not made Sinners before? what excess were it to justifie those to eternal life; that were never condemned to eternal death? let him look to it, either <HI>Christ</HI> must be preferred in these Acts and Excesses, or else his Attributes are but impaired. (Conseq.) <HI>That the judgement which came from</HI> Adams <HI>sin, unto the condem∣nation
<PB N="88" REF="51"/>
of the world, was nothing but tem∣poral Death, is here affirmed.</HI> (In con∣seq. so far is it from being affirmed that upon right deduction, it is more than once denied. For it was <HI>Death</HI> entring by <HI>Sin,</HI> and that was something more than temporal death; It was <HI>Death reigning,</HI> and that was something more than death temporal; It was death opposed to the <HI>justification of life,</HI> and that must be something more than <HI>tem∣poral death</HI>; It was death opposed to <HI>reigning in life,</HI> and therefore must needs be more than temporal death. (Conseq.) <HI>It is in no sence imaginable, that the death which here St.</HI> Paul <HI>says passed upon all men, and which reigned from</HI> Adam <HI>to</HI> Moses, <HI>should be eterual Death. (Inconseq.)</HI> Will he allow no man a sensible imagination, besides his own understanding? or rather a sensible understanding besides his own imagina∣tion? <HI>Death passed upon all men,</HI> that is eternal death passed upon all men, ac∣cording to the justice of the sentence, and their due desert, There's one sense. That Death which reigned from <HI>Adam</HI> to <HI>Moses,</HI> was eternal death; for if you take the time of <HI>Deaths reigning</HI>
<PB N="89" REF="51"/>
to be betwixt them two, terminally and exclusively, then was it not so much as a tempotal death passing upon all men; But death reigns not but from an eternal Law, and in and to eternity. There's a∣nother sense, yea Death reigned from <HI>Adam</HI> to <HI>Moses,</HI> and so onward <HI>until Christ,</HI> and would have reigned eter∣nally over all men, had not Christ ta∣ken it off. There's another sense. (<HI>Con∣seq.</HI>) <HI>the Apostle speaks of that death which was threatned to</HI> Adam. (<HI>Incon∣seq.</HI>) rather of the death which was threatned to the world in <HI>Adam,</HI> but take it as directed to <HI>Adams person, dy∣ing thou shalt die,</HI> Gen. 2. 17. The sa∣cred idiom serves to note the continuity, as well as the certainty of <HI>Death</HI>: and that was an intimation of the eternity. (Conseq.) <HI>The Apostle means such a Death which was afterwards threatned In</HI> Moses <HI>Law.</HI> (Inconseq.) well, but who takes a temporal death only? nay, who takes not an eternal death chiefly to be threatned upon the breach of the Mor∣ral Law? (Conseq.) <HI>and such a death which fell even upon the most righteous of Adams posterity.</HI> (Inconseq.) True it fell upon them in part, not that the other
<PB N="90" REF="52"/>
part was not due unto them, but that it was taken off by <HI>Christ.</HI> (Conseq.) <HI>Upon the most righteous of</HI> Adam's <HI>poste∣rity, who did not sin after the similitude of</HI> Adam's <HI>transgression.</HI> (Inconseq.) Such righteous ones of all his posterity were never yet known. <HI>Abel, Seth,</HI> and <HI>Methusala</HI> were certainly none such; for they and their like (even all the holy Pa∣triarks) were sinners, as well by imita∣tion, as by propagation; and sinned as well actually as originally. To say that those holy men sin not after the simili∣tude of <HI>Adams transgression,</HI> in that they sinned less, alas! that's but poor; for so even wicked men are said, not to sin after the similitude of one another. (Conseq.) <HI>Because in proportion to the e∣vil, so was the imputation of the Sin, it follows, That</HI> Adam's <HI>sin is ours me∣tonimycally and improperly.</HI> (Inconseq.) Here's nothing at all which follows a∣right: for even the first part of his argu∣ment is preposterous: By <HI>evil</HI> he in∣tends punishment, and then the conse∣quence is quite contrary, because the sin was not imputed in proportion to the punishment; but indeed the punishment was deputed in proportion to the Sin.
<PB N="91" REF="52"/>
And therefore it must follow (by reason of contraries) That <HI>Adams</HI> sin was not tropically and tralatitiously, but even litterally and properly ours. But con∣sider what he says in effect; That God did measure the sin according to the pu∣nishment. Now good Lord! how can the Divine Attributes stand safe to such a saying? for what Justice is that, that regulates or proportions the sin by the punishment, and not the punishment by the Sin? In the imputation of God or men, who makes the sin to follow the punishment, and not rather the punish∣ment to follow the sin? But say his rule stood upon some right foot; yet how follows his argument from it? The Sin was imputed in proportion to the pu∣nishment; but the punishment was pro∣per and real, not figurative and equi∣vocal; and therefore so must the Sin be too: else who can tell what's become of all this proportion? (Conseq.) <HI>God was not finally angry with us, nor had so much as any designs of eternal displeasure upon that account.</HI> (Inconseq.) The way to vindicate Gods Attributes, is, not to pry into them too curiously; nor to de∣termine upon them too peremptorily:
<PB N="92" REF="53"/>
nor to aggravate them too severe∣ly, nor to extenuate them too indul∣gently, but to believe them and ju∣stifie them, and magnifie them, so as they are revealed. God indeed was not finally angry with us (his Elect) nei∣ther upon our original, nor upon our a∣ctual account: And why? because his wrath was so appeased by <HI>Christ,</HI> satis∣faction. But was he not therefore so at the Sin simply and absolutely conside∣red? if he had no design of eternal dis∣pleasure, upon that account, then he sent <HI>Christ</HI> to die in vain. For <HI>Christ</HI> died to prevent, not the temporal, but the eternal death; Nor was that to re∣deem us from the mortality and conditi∣on of our Nature (for he suffered it him∣self, and left us to follow him in a con∣formity) but from the depravation and damnation of it. (Conseq.) <HI>This an∣ger went no further than the evils of this life; and therefore the imputation was not of a proper guilt; for that might justly have past beyond our grave, if the same had past beyond a Metonymie or a juridi∣cal external imputation.</HI> (Inconseq.) O rare consequent! the punishment was
<PB N="93" REF="53"/>
but temporally inflicted, and therefore the Sin was not properly imputed. As if temporal punishments (whether from God, or men) were the arguments of improper Sins only. But O wonderfull vertue of a bare Trope, or figurative locution! to qualifie such a pravity, ex∣tenuate such a provocation, divert such a desert, yea to regulate such a Justice, or to restrain and limit such a power. If his Metonymical imputation be the same with <HI>Iuridical</HI> and <HI>external,</HI> then (me thinks) this proportion should be ob∣served in the proceeding, That as the Sin is imputed but only as it were in some shadow or resemblance of words; so should the punishment be inflicted, and not in any deed or substance. For he that is found guilty, but only in an imaginary <HI>Idea</HI> or picture, ought not to be executed, but only in conceit, or as it were in <HI>effigie.</HI> But I am forbidden to smile, since it is a matter of fighing, in regard the Divine Attributes are so stricken at: For what provocation can there be for Gods universal and continu∣al anger (for such it is against the Fall and original sin) without an, mputati∣on of a proper and participating guilt?
<PB N="94" REF="54"/>
where the sin is properly imputed, there (he grants) the punishment may justly goe beyond our Graves, that is even to <HI>Hell.</HI> But if there be no such imputati∣on, no such propriety, no such partici∣pation; I can see no cause why those e∣vils should passe so far as this present life. Eternal death is little enough, if sin be properly and particularly impu∣ted: but if it be not so, I cannot see but that even a temporal death to all man∣kind, must be too much. (Conseq.) <HI>That as no man ever imposed penance for it</HI> (for original Sin) <HI>so God himself in nature, did never for it afflict or affright the Conscience.</HI> (Inconseq.) By pe∣nance surely he understands not private Repentance, but publick Discipline, or that of the Churches imposing; say it were so, the Churches power is to im∣pose the penance for publike, notorious, scandalous and exemplary Crimes and offences: it cannot take cognisance (as no external Law or administration can) of an inward, secret, unsearchable, (though worthily suspected) Sin, such as the Original is. Besides, whose should be the authority in such a cause or case, where all are concluded, and confest
<PB N="95" REF="54"/>
guilty alike? As for the other part, I ask of him, did not <HI>God</HI> himself afflict and affright <HI>Adams</HI> Conscience for it, when he was forced to say; <HI>I heard thy voice in the Garden, and I was afraid, because I was naked, and I hid my self. Gen.</HI> 3. 10. And we all feel and must confesse, this afflicting this affrighting was not of his person only, but in his and our Nature also; as woefull expe∣rience convinces us all to this very day. (Conseq.) <HI>And why, the conscience shall be for ever at so much peace for this sin, that a man shall never give one groan for his share of guilt in</HI> Adams <HI>sin, unlesse some or other scares him with an impertinent proposition.</HI> (Inconseq.) What the con∣science shall be for ever, is hard for him to say; And for what it hath been hitherto, he knows a Conscience is not always to be argued for pure and free, because it is quiet and still. But what says he to <HI>David</HI>? did not he groan for it in that <HI>Poenitential</HI> of his? <HI>Behold I was shapen in iniquity, and in sin hath my Mother conceived me,</HI> Psalm 51. 5. And to St. <HI>Paul,</HI> is this no groaning,? <HI>Oh wretched man that I am, who shall deli∣ver me from the body of this death?</HI> Rom.
<PB N="96" REF="55"/>
7. 24. Nay shall we not beleeve what he but lately said of himself? <HI>For my part I cannot but confesse that to be which I feel and groan under, and by which all the world is miserable.</HI> Let him look to his Conscience, and see how his words agree first and last; I hope he will not now say it was some <HI>impertinent proposi∣tion</HI> that scared him thereunto. (<HI>Con∣seq.</HI>) <HI>Why the Conscience should not natu∣rally be afflicted for it, nor so much as naturally know it, I confesse I cannot yet make any reasonable conjecture, save this only; that it is not properly a Sin, but on∣ly Metonymically and improperly.</HI> (In∣conseq.) Such a conjecture is not reaso∣nable; for if to deny a Sin to be such, were sufficient, because the Conscience naturally smiles not for it, nor yet con∣vinces of it: so many actual sins might easily come to be denied. A strange con∣jecture for a figurative appellation to save a Conscience. I know the Consci∣ence can Syllogize, but I never knew that she could ever so Rhetoricate with her self: such a conjecture is so far from being worth the sole preferring, that it's not worth the naming, where better reasons are brought forth. As namely,
<PB N="97" REF="55"/>
That Original sin her self has blinded and bedulled the Conscience, as touch∣ing the true and full apprehension of her self, and of Original sin. That the law and light of nature is exceedingly obscu∣red to all Consciences since the <HI>Fall</HI> That most mens Consciences are insensi∣ble even of their actual and sensual sins; how much more then of the Original and invisible? That men have pulled and seared both their own, and others Consciences, as touching the true sense of Original Sin, by dayly hatching and broaching such <HI>heresies</HI> and errors about it: No marvel then that men are here so insensible; we see it may easily come to passe through natural ignorance and ill habits, without this diminishing glass of a <HI>Metonymical</HI> spectacle. (Conseq.) <HI>there are some whole Churches which think themselves so little concerned in the matter of Original Sin, that they have not a word of it in all their Theologue.</HI> (Inconseq.) That they have not a word of it, their Theologue is defective to them, that they think themselves not concerned in it, they are defective to their <HI>Theologie.</HI> I could tell him of some Churches that in their <HI>Theologie</HI>
<PB N="98" REF="56"/>
make no mention of the <HI>Decalogue</HI>; do they therefore think themselves but lit∣tle concerned in it? again some Chur∣ches think themselves so much concern∣ed in Original Sin, that they beleeve Souls, as well as Bodies, to be propaga∣ted from <HI>Adam.</HI> I spake this of the <HI>E∣thiopians</HI> and the <HI>Russians,</HI> no Church but is bound to have such a body of Di∣vinity as may comprehend the whole principles of <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Religion</HI>; yea, and to unfold them, and confess them so far as they are revealed in the word of God; but what is it to object some ob∣scure and confused Churches, to the Ca∣tholique universal, &amp; to the most order∣ly and eminent <HI>Churches</HI> of the <HI>World</HI>? (Conseq.) <HI>The height of this imagina∣tion hath wrought so high in the Church of</HI> Rome, <HI>that when they would doe great honour to the Virgin</HI> Mary, <HI>they were pleased to allow unto her an immaculate conception, without any Original Sin.</HI> (Inconseq.) So far as the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> seemed to joyn with the Pri∣mitive Churches in the point of Ori∣ginal Sin, so far also have the Reform∣ed Churches joyned with them, as namely, That Original Sin is, That it
<PB N="99" REF="56"/>
is properly and inherently a Sin. That it descendeth by natural propagation, not by imitation. That it hath in both a stain and guilt. That it subjected to misery and death in all senses and signi∣fications: That we are redeemed there∣from by the merits of <HI>Christ</HI>: These are heights indeed, but not heights of ima∣gination, but sound Doctrine. And these she pretended to hold forth against all those who affirmed, That <HI>Adam</HI> lost Original righteousnesse only for himself, and not for us his posterity: and that by <HI>Adams</HI> disobedience sin de∣scended not upon Mankind, but only a bodily death or punishment. Indeed here she hath also some heights of ima∣gination, as, That Original sin is not only remitted by Baptism, but utterly abolished and quite taken away. That the concupiscence remaining in the rege∣nerate, is no sin. That Original Sin is only in the inferiour, and not in the superiour faculties. That the blessed Virgin was conceived and born free from Original Sin, yea, and many more heights of imagination they have much disputed on among their Schola∣sticks, so that they owe their errors,
<PB N="100" REF="57"/>
not to the simple profession of Original Sinne, but to their subtle disputation about it. As for their opinion of the blessed Virgins immaculate conception, it arose from no other height, but that o<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their own <HI>superstition,</HI> which is too no∣torious, in all they can feign or imagin<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for her, say of her, or doe to her. But I pray God this low imagination, o<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> slender and slight conceit of a <HI>Metony∣mical, juridical, external collateral,</HI> nay, equivocal, abusive, phantastical imputa∣tion, serve not to be get a conceit or pre∣sumption of an immaculate conception in us all. I have read of one that would needs deny the immortality of the Soul, with intent to disprove the Popish pur∣gatory; but there are other ways to re∣fute this Error of the immaculate con∣ception, than by abating the truth or utmost truth of Original Sin.</P>
<P><HI>One thing more</HI> (he saith) <HI>I am to ob∣serve before I leave considering the word of the Apostle.</HI> This one thing is not so much a consequent of what he would say for himself, as an argument against all such as would argue against him. The ground betwixt both is laid in these last words of the <HI>Apostle, As by one mans dis∣obedience
<PB N="101" REF="57"/>
many were made Sinners, so by the obedience of one, shall many be made righteous.</HI> Some (saith he) from hence suppose they argue strongly to the over∣throw of all that I have said, Thus, <HI>As by Christ we are made really righteous, so by Adam we are made really sinners.</HI> This we acknowledge not only to be our Argument, but our way of <HI>Augmenta∣tion</HI>; and if this standing good be suffi∣cient to overthrow all that he hath said, then it is easie to be observed to what purpose he hath spoken all this while, but to this he hath spoken in his <HI>Addres∣ses,</HI> and to them we can say nothing till we see them. <HI>But besides</HI> (saith he) <HI>I have something very material to reply to the form of the Argument, which is a ve∣ry trick and fallacy.</HI> Strong reason may be spoken very often without a formal <HI>Syllogisme</HI>; and where the matter cannot be denied to be true and good, 'tis but a kind of <HI>sophistical fallacy</HI> to stand too pedantically upon the form. — <HI>But to argue from hence, (as by Christ we are made really righteous, so by</HI> Adam <HI>we are made really sinners</HI>) <HI>is</HI> (saith he) <HI>to invert the purpose of the Apostle.</HI> The reciprocation or conversion of proposi∣tions
<PB N="102" REF="58"/>
is no inversion of their purpose, where they may truly praedicate either way. Neither is the inverting of words in their order, always a perverting of them in their intent. <HI>But the Apostle argues from the lesse to the greater.</HI> In∣deed the Apostle in his comparison pro∣ceeds after such a manner, as from <HI>A∣dam</HI> to <HI>Christ,</HI> from <HI>Sin</HI> to <HI>Grace,</HI> from <HI>Death</HI> to <HI>Life</HI>: now Comparates (<HI>Ia∣nus</HI>-like) look <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, for∣wards and backwards, and may argue mutually from one to another, Nay they must doe it, else could they not be Com∣parates; now though the Apostle argue from the lesse to the greater, by way of Amplification: yet he forbids not to ar∣gue from the greater to the lesse, for matter of reallity, and that is all our Argument. <HI>But we</HI> (saith he) <HI>make it conclude affirmatively from the greater to the lesse, in matter of power.</HI> Will he allow us to doe it negatively? why that will serve our turn sufficiently. Thus, As <HI>Christ's</HI> righteousnesse was not imputed only: so neither was <HI>Adams</HI> sin; or thus, As our righte∣ousness by Christ was not a <HI>Metonymi∣cal</HI> righteousnesse; so our sin by <HI>Adam</HI>
<PB N="103" REF="58"/>
was not a <HI>Metonymical</HI> Sin. But (by his leave) we may take liberty to argue affir∣matively, as before, &amp; yet offend against no <HI>Logical</HI> Law, or Canon of Comparates, nay and the consequence shall be of great force, even affirmatively, as Thus. As <HI>Christ</HI> did and suffered his Fathers will; so ought we to doe and suffer the same. As God charged his Angels with Folly, how much more may he us mor∣tal men? and from the Apostle in this place. As the Life was a real life, so the Death was a real Death: As the Grace was real Grace, so the Sin was real Sin. But he now assumes the trick or fallacy himself, taxing us for conclu∣ding affirmatively from the greater to the lesse <HI>in matter of power</HI> (as what a <HI>Man</HI> can doe, a <HI>Child</HI> can doe; What God is able to doe, &amp;c. the Devil is able to doe, &amp;c.) Whereas our manner of arguing is not in matter of power and prevalency; but for matter of being, and reallity. Now betwixt the greater and the lesse, though there may be a disproportionate <HI>action,</HI> yet there must be some proportionate <HI>being.</HI> And what is affirmed of the greater, may likewise be affirmed of the lesser, and
<PB N="104" REF="59"/>
that in the same kind and manner, al∣though not according to the same mea∣sure or degree; yea <HI>very Opposites</HI> and and <HI>Disparates</HI> if they come to be com∣pared, are accepted as opposite and dif∣ferent only in their proper forms and adjuncts, but alike, and agreeing in their common Attributes, according to which they are compared; and without which there could be no ground for compari∣son. And where there is no ground for Collation; there can be no cause for prelation; as here in the Apostles worlds; Take away the reallity of Sin, and the Proper being of the <HI>offence,</HI> and in such a comparison, with what excesse, or excellency, can the <HI>Grace,</HI> the <HI>Free-gift, Iustification,</HI> and the <HI>righteousnesse of Christ</HI> be preferred thereunto? There's nothing now remaining, but to put it into an <HI>Hypothetical Syllogism,</HI> and so to leave it concluding without all <HI>Fallacy,</HI> according to his own conditi∣on, <HI>viz.</HI> If we be made really righte∣ous by <HI>Christ,</HI> then we were made really Sinners by <HI>Adam</HI>: But we are made re∣ally righteous by <HI>Christ, Ergo</HI></P>
<P>And thus (worthy Sir) though I can∣not presume my self to be one of <HI>those
<PB N="105" REF="59"/>
wise persons</HI> he speaks of; yet this I pre∣sume, that I am not <HI>unwarily perswaded</HI> by this way of arguing; neither can I (out of my simplicity) observe that it is this way, but rather his own whole way of arguing that appears <HI>unconclu∣ding.</HI> But let it be with your own judge∣ment how we either of us appear to you, from what we have said.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>2. For the Church.</HEAD>
<P>TO this objection, That his Do∣ctrine is against the 9th. <HI>Article</HI> in the <HI>Church of England.</HI> He saith, <HI>I have already answered it in some additio∣nal Papers, which are already published.</HI> I would I might have had the opportunity to have seen them, supposing they may contain some kind of Apologie, which might have saved me the labour of an Additional in this latter part. But for what I here see he must give me leave for to speak, as that he may see, That (in judgement, though not in Charity) we are Two. His zeal for the <HI>Church
<PB N="106" REF="60"/>
of England,</HI> seems to be such and so much, that he is protesting before hand, against all that shall but seem to suspect it. But he is indigning him in especial that shall take upon him to tax him for it, in the least degree. I hope this will not overprovoke his patience, only to intreat him; First to reconcile his own understanding to his <HI>subscription</HI>; and then, his own words, to the words of the <HI>Article.</HI></P>
<P>(<HI>First</HI>) A faithfull subscription of a dutifull Son of the Church, is to sub∣mit his understanding, and consent sim∣ply unto her suffrage. And to under∣write (with hand and heart) her <HI>Arti∣cles</HI> and <HI>Canons,</HI> accepted in their plain literal sense; And not to bring to them, nor yet reserve from them, any other understanding or intention of his own. Laws (we say) are to be interpreted and accepted, according to the mind of the Law-givers; and a promissary Oath ought to be performed, according to the intention of him to whom the pro∣mise is made. Now for him to say, <HI>I have oftentimes subscribed that Article,</HI> and, <HI>I am ready a thousand times to sub∣scribe that Article,</HI> and yet to say a∣gain:
<PB N="107" REF="60"/>
<HI>I doe not understand the words of that Article, as most men doe, but I understand them, as they can be true, and as they can very fairly signi∣fie, and as they agree with the word of God, and right reason,</HI> What kind of subscription call you this? with such a liberty or reservation a man might have (without all scruple) taken the <HI>Prote∣station,</HI> the <HI>Covenant,</HI> the <HI>Engagement,</HI> or an <HI>Oath</HI> of <HI>Abjuration.</HI> But whom means he by those <HI>most men</HI>? certainly not the Adversaries of the Church, who refuse to subscribe them: But the Sons of the Church, his brethren, who have subscribed them as well as he. The Ad∣versaries, though they consent (for the most part) to the Doctrine, yet they refuse to subscribe the <HI>Article,</HI> meerly because it is <HI>our Churches.</HI> But as it is the <HI>Churches,</HI> so, we that are Sons and Brethren, doe (with one understanding) simply subscribe it, nor doe we make our own conditions, by way of excepti∣on; but we take them all in an undoubt∣ed concession. For we also understand the words of the <HI>Article,</HI> as they can be true, and as they can fairly signifie, and that is even in their literal and gramma∣tical
<PB N="108" REF="61"/>
sense. And likewise as they agree with the Word of God and right rea∣son, for so we suppose them in the sense aforesaid. And although we confesse, with him, that the <HI>Church used an in∣comparable wisdom and temper</HI> in com∣posing her <HI>Articles,</HI> both with respect to <HI>New-reformists</HI> and <HI>Non-conformists</HI> too, notwithstanding we believe her <HI>Prudence</HI> and <HI>Piety</HI> was such, that she intended not so to secure the outward <HI>Peace</HI> of the <HI>Church</HI> against either, as that the <HI>Truth</HI> of it (in either part) might be prejudiced thereby, much less that she contrived any thing in such a <HI>charitable latitude,</HI> as to give license to any, for passing the rectitude, and ar∣ctitude of <HI>Verity,</HI> or that any one should presume upon his private and dis∣sentaneous opinion, notwithstanding her publique and unanimous Judgement. It was discovered by some of themselves, that when <HI>the Councel of Trent</HI> com∣pleated her <HI>Canons</HI> of Original Sin, and many particulars of them appearing so consonant to the <HI>Scriptures,</HI> and to <HI>Or∣thodox</HI> Antiquity; yet they studied to compile the whole with such Artifice, as that notwithstanding they might
<PB N="109" REF="61"/>
leave to their own <HI>Scholasticks</HI> a liberty of disputing and opining what they pleased: But I trust the like shall never be said of the <HI>Church of England,</HI> either as touching this, or any other of her <HI>Articles</HI>; and for my part, I conceive it to be a truer part of a Son of the <HI>Church,</HI> rather to restrain his sense, to her words, than to strain or enlarge her words, to his own sense.</P>
<P>(<HI>Secondly,</HI>) As concerning this <HI>Ar∣ticle</HI> of <HI>Original birth,</HI> or <HI>Sin,</HI> or <HI>Birth-Sin,</HI> in as much as he says, <HI>if I had cause to dissent from it, I would certain∣ly doe it in those just measures which my duty on the one side, and the interest of truth on the other would require of me.</HI> Hereupon I am very willing to beleeve him on his own word, as liking exceeding well of his ingenious Confes∣sion: <HI>I have no cause to disagree,</HI> and not much misliking his resolution, <HI>I will not suffer my self to be supposed to be of a differing judgement from my dear Mother, which is the best Church of the world.</HI> Wherefore I shall doe no more (which is the least that can be done in an appearing difference) but set down the words of the <HI>Article,</HI> and then his
<PB N="110" REF="62"/>
own words in the <HI>Antithesis,</HI> And so leave it to himself (according to his own pro∣mised temper and measure) to reconcile them. Neither wil I so much as once ima∣gine, that he hath less zeal for our <HI>Church</HI> than my self, that so I may spare him the labour of a fruitlesse vow; <HI>in being all his life confuting me.</HI> Let him but shew how his own sayings are conform∣able, or not repugnant to what the <HI>Ar∣ticle</HI> saith (which to me and many others seem so contrary) and we two have done, nay are (as we were) in Faith and love of <HI>Christians,</HI> one. But if he goe otherwise to work, I must take the confidence to tell him; he may <HI>be all his life confuting,</HI> and not confute.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="article">
<HEAD>Article.</HEAD>
<P>— <HI>Original Sin standeth not in the following of</HI> Adam, <HI>as the</HI> Pelagians <HI>do vainly talk.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="antithesis">
<HEAD>Antithesis.</HEAD>
<P>All actual Sins doe not proceed from this Sin of <HI>Adam,</HI> pag. 47. — liberty and not <HI>Adams</HI> Sin is the cause of all our
<PB N="111" REF="62"/>
actual, pag. 49. — From the first <HI>Adam</HI> nothing descended to us — but an evil example, page. 80. not direct Sins to us in their natural abode, — but princi∣ples of Sin to us in their emanation, <HI>pag.</HI> 81. who by imitation of his Transgres∣sion on the stock of their own natural choice, did sin against God.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="article">
<HEAD>Article.</HEAD>
<P><HI>But it is the fault and corruption of the nature of every man that natu∣rally is ingendred of the off-spring of</HI> Adam.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="antithesis">
<HEAD>Antithesis.</HEAD>
<P>The guilt of this Sin being imputed, the same is conveyed to all their Poste∣rity by ordinary generation — this heap of errors pag. 29, 30. — Naturally it cannot be, <HI>pag.</HI> 32. — not that we bring it upon our shoulders into the world with us, pag. 78.— if God hath given us a Nature by <HI>derivation</HI> which is whol∣ly corrupted, &amp;c. <HI>pag.</HI> 96.— that <HI>A∣dams</HI> Sin is ours <HI>Metonymically</HI> and im∣prope<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rly, <HI>pag.</HI> 127.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="article">
<PB N="112" REF="63"/>
<HEAD>Article.</HEAD>
<P>— <HI>Whereby man is very far gon from Original righteousness; and is of his own nature inclined to evil, so that the Flesh lusteth always, contra∣ry to the Spirit.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="antithesis">
<HEAD>Antithesis.</HEAD>
<P>The evil did so descend upon us, that we were left in powers and capaci∣ties to serve and glorifie God, pag. 16. — That by this Sin our first Parents fell from their Original righteousness, &amp;c. this heap of errors, &amp;c. pag. 29, 30. I can by no means approve that by this we are disabled and made opposite to all good, and wholly inclined to all evil, pag. 39. — his nature was not spoiled by that Sin, he was not wholly inclined to all evil, pag. 40, 46, 47.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="article">
<HEAD>Article.</HEAD>
<P><HI>And therefore in every person born into this world it deserveth Gods wrath, and Damnation.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="antithesis">
<PB N="113" REF="63"/>
<HEAD>Antithesis.</HEAD>
<P>Original Sin doth — in its own Na∣ture bring guilt upon the Sinner, where∣by he is bound over to the wrath of God, &amp;c. — this heap of Errors, pag. 30. It cannot be just for God to damn us, for being in a state of calamity, to which state we entred no way but by his con∣stitution and decree pag. 38. — if it be intollerable to damn Children for the Sin of <HI>Adam,</HI> then it is intollerable to say it is damnable, pag. 59. — Is it a∣gainst Gods goodness that Infants should be damn'd for Original Sin? &amp;c. pag. 67. — It is against Gods Justice to damn us for the fault of another, pag. 63. Children born in Christ, and not in <HI>Adam,</HI> &amp;c. pag. 74. — born beloved, and quitted from wrath, &amp;c. pag. 75. — born in the accounts of the Divine favour, pag. 77. — if God decrees us to be born Sinners, &amp;c. if God does damn any for that, &amp;c. pag. 94. — if God does cast Infants into Hell for the Sin of others, &amp;c. pag. 96. — It is impossible that the greatest part of mankind should be left in the eternal bonds of Hell, by <HI>A∣dam,</HI>
<PB N="114" REF="64"/>
pag. 125. — The Judgement which for <HI>Adams</HI> Sin came into the con∣demnation of the world, was nothing but temporal death. pag. 126.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="article">
<HEAD>Article.</HEAD>
<P><HI>And this infection of Nature doth re∣main, yea in them that are regenera∣ted, whereby the lust of the flesh, &amp;c.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="antithesis">
<HEAD>Antithesis.</HEAD>
<P>The corruption of nature remains in the regenerate, &amp;c. this heap of errors, pag. 29, 30. — I can by no means ap∣prove that our natural corruption in the regenerate still remains, and is still pro∣perly a Sin. pag. 39. — That our natu∣ral corruption in the regenerate still re∣mains, and is still a Sin, and properly a Sin, I have (I confesse) heartily oppo∣sed it, &amp;c. pag. 49. 52.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="article">
<HEAD>Article.</HEAD>
<P><HI>And although there is no condemna∣tion for them that believe, and are bap∣tized; yet the Apostle doth confesse,
<PB N="115" REF="64"/>
that concupiscence and lust, hath of it self the nature of Sin.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="antithesis">
<HEAD>Antithesis:</HEAD>
<P>This will follow, that <HI>Adam's</HI> Sinne hath done some mischief that the grace of Christ can never cure, though it be pardoned and mortified, yet still re∣mains, and is still a Sin, is perfect Non-sense, pag. 51. — we are rescued from <HI>Adam</HI> before we were born, else <HI>Adam's</HI> Sin prevailed really in some periods, and by some effects for which God in <HI>Christ</HI> had provided no remedy, pag. 74. — It is a Sin <HI>Metonymically,</HI> and just so in <HI>Baptism</HI> it is taken away, pag. 103.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="section">
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q>Qui Ecclesiae renititur, et restitit; in Ecclesiàse esse confidit?</Q>
<BIBL>Cyprian de simp. Praelat.</BIBL>
</EPIGRAPH>
<DIV2 TYPE="letter">
<OPENER>SIR,</OPENER>
<P>BE pleased to know that all the errors which have been about Original Sin, have risen chiefly through want of
<PB N="116" REF="65"/>
a perfect <HI>Definition,</HI> or compleat <HI>De∣scription</HI> of it, some (and they not the least <HI>Hereticks</HI>) have contended against all definition; others have been so vari∣ous in defining, and so incompleat in describing, that they have administred but matter unto more contention. I am perswaded that out of this place in the 5 to the <HI>Romans</HI>; a perfect <HI>Definition, or very compleat Description</HI> might be made, and that such as might compre∣hend both the name and nature, and subject and derivation, and cause and effects, and remedy; My short time, and shorter abilities will not now suffer me to venture upon it. I have done my Task; and (I hope in some part) an∣swered my Title, and your expectati∣on, such as I cou<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, or could so sudden∣ly make it. I send it humbly to your hands, and through them (if you think meet) to the world. All that I will now say of this <HI>Author</HI> is this, <HI>That he hath erred learnedly,</HI> far unlike the many senselesse and scurrilous <HI>Hereticks</HI> and <HI>Schismaticks</HI> of this our exulcerated age. And I hope his own learning will let him see his Error. Otherwise, he must think others are not so unlearned,
<PB N="117" REF="65"/>
as for him to impose upon them. Ra∣ther than so, I could most heartily wish one more learned in the <HI>Truth</HI> than my self may yet more particularly under∣take him. To you, Sir, I need say no∣thing, you are known. And for my self I need say as little to you; you know,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir, <HI>Your Minister Friend, and Servant,</HI></SALUTE>
<SIGNED>JOHN GAULE.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

